<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Westrow revived. A funerall poem without fiction. / Composed by Geo: Wither Esq. That God may be glorified in his saints; that the memory of Thomas Westrow Esq; may be preserved, and that others by his exemplary life and death may be drawn to imitation of his vertues. Blest are the dead who dye in Christ; for, from their labours they do rest; and, whether they do live or dye, his saints are precious in his eye.</title>
            <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96786</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1479_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208732</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867655</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119976</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96786)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119976)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 190:E1479[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Westrow revived. A funerall poem without fiction. / Composed by Geo: Wither Esq. That God may be glorified in his saints; that the memory of Thomas Westrow Esq; may be preserved, and that others by his exemplary life and death may be drawn to imitation of his vertues. Blest are the dead who dye in Christ; for, from their labours they do rest; and, whether they do live or dye, his saints are precious in his eye.</title>
                  <author>Wither, George, 1588-1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 70 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by F: Neile in Aldersgatestreet:,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan. 3.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Westrow, Thomas --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elegaic poetry, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119976:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119976:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>WESTROW</hi> REVIVED.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Funerall Poem</hi> without <hi>Fiction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compoſed by <hi>Geo: Wither</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq.</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>GOD</hi> may be glorified in his <hi>Saints;</hi> That the memory of <hi>Thomas Weſtrow</hi> Eſq; may be preſerved, and that others by his exemplary <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> may be drawn to imitation of his <hi>Vertues.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Bleſt are the <hi>Dead</hi> who dye in CHRIST;</l>
               <l>For, from their Labours they do reſt;</l>
               <l>And, whether they do <hi>live</hi> or <hi>dye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Saints</hi> are precious in his eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <hi>READER,</hi> peruſe <hi>this</hi> thorow: For, to <hi>Thee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It moſt pertains, though <hi>WESTROW</hi> named be;</l>
               <l>And, gives <hi>(as by the way)</hi> ſome ſhort <hi>hints,</hi> there,</l>
               <l>To what <hi>Intents,</hi> He, chiefly doth appear,</l>
               <l>And whereof, if good heed ſhall not be took</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Somwhat,</hi> ere long, more fully will be ſpoke.</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Prophets,</hi> many a day</l>
               <l>Have ſpoken; and a <hi>Greater one</hi> then they.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hear them:</hi> For when <hi>GOD</hi> ſendeth by the <hi>DEAD,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His <hi>Meſſages</hi> will come with much more <hi>Dread</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then <hi>Comfort;</hi> and few men; with good effect,</l>
               <l>Shall hear <hi>theſe,</hi> the <hi>former</hi> do neglect.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be wiſe,</hi> or elſe; But, Ile, now ſay no more,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Feet of meſſengers are at the door.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>F: Neile</hi> in Alderſgateſtreet: 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119976:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119976:2"/>
            <head>WESTROVV REVIVED.</head>
            <div n="1" type="canto">
               <head>The firſt <hi>CANTO.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Authors <hi>muſings here are ſhown</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Night, <hi>ere ought, to him was known</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Weſtrowes <hi>death; whereof, the</hi> Morrow</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aſſur'd him, to his greater ſorrow:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then, that which he hath more to ſay,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is put off, to another day.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>TWas <hi>midnight;</hi> and, I had <hi>my ſelf</hi> undreſt,</l>
                  <l>In hope, the <hi>nights</hi> remainder, for my reſt</l>
                  <l>Had been allowd; and, in that hope, all thoſe</l>
                  <l>Diſtractings, which my <hi>minde</hi> might diſcompoſe</l>
                  <l>Quite threw aſide, and haſtned to the place,</l>
                  <l>Where, that <hi>refreſhment,</hi> offer'd an embrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, in <hi>ſleeps</hi> poſture, ere I down was laid,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Thought,</hi> within my heart, ſtart up, and ſaid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weſtrowe,</hi> thy beſt, and moſt deſerving <hi>Friend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lies feeble, and approaching to his end,</l>
                  <l>By thee unviſited (though two days, now</l>
                  <l>Are paſt, ſince of his <hi>weakneſs</hi> thou didſt know.)</l>
                  <l>How, canſt thou anſwer ſuch a groſſe neglecting,</l>
                  <l>Of one, ſo well, ſo truly thee affecting?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A ſecond <hi>Thought</hi> thus anſwer'd thereunto,</l>
                  <l>(To make amends) to <hi>morrow</hi> I will go</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119976:3"/>
                  <l>In hope, (ſince I, for this <hi>neglect</hi> am griev'd)</l>
                  <l>A juſt <hi>excuſe,</hi> will kindly be receiv'd;</l>
                  <l>And, that <hi>Love-reall,</hi> ſhall not through <hi>defect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That's accidental, ſuffer by <hi>ſuſpect.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To <hi>morrow,</hi> ſaid a third <hi>thought,</hi> comes too late;</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Lifes Commiſſion,</hi> is quite out of date;</l>
                  <l>And, that, which might have been enjoy'd to <hi>day,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is, by <hi>procraſtination,</hi> loſt for aye.</l>
                  <l>Thou, too too long, thy <hi>purpoſe</hi> haſt forbore,</l>
                  <l>And, never now, ſhalt <hi>hear,</hi> or <hi>ſee</hi> him more.</l>
                  <l>Yet, be not grieved, that it happens thus,</l>
                  <l>For, he is ſafe. And, as good <hi>Lazarus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Loſt nothing, by a ſickneſs unto death,</l>
                  <l>Save only that ſuſpention of his breath</l>
                  <l>For ſome few days, which did a means provide,</l>
                  <l>Whereby, both GOD, and <hi>he,</hi> were glorifide</l>
                  <l>In greater meaſure; ſo, it may, be thou,</l>
                  <l>Shalt hereby, have <hi>occaſions</hi> offered, now,</l>
                  <l>Of that, whereby, hereafter may be made</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Advantages,</hi> which could not elſe be had.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Advantages!</hi> cride out, another <hi>Thought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alas! what good <hi>effect</hi> can forth be brought</l>
                  <l>By ſuch an <hi>Accident,</hi> if I ſhall hear</l>
                  <l>That, to be true, which yet, is but my <hi>fear?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How can my <hi>pretermiſſion</hi> ought produce</l>
                  <l>Of any future comfortable uſe?</l>
                  <l>Or, to what likely profitable end,</l>
                  <l>Can ſuch a comfortles <hi>privation</hi> tend?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In <hi>Fancies</hi> Tenneſcourt, thus, to and fro</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Thoughts</hi> were toſt, and plaid at <hi>hazzard</hi> ſo,</l>
                  <l>That very much diſtemper'd I became,</l>
                  <l>With that unlook'd for, and unpleaſing <hi>game.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſilent Dialogue</hi> made ſuch impreſſions</l>
                  <l>Upon my heart, and ſo inhanc'd my <hi>paſſion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, all the night enſuing they did keep</l>
                  <l>My <hi>mind</hi> on him, and bard mine eyes from ſleep.</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119976:3"/>
                  <l>I, likewiſe, have ſo frequently perceiv'd</l>
                  <l>My ſouls <hi>preſagings</hi> true, that <hi>I</hi> beleev'd</l>
                  <l>This ſad <hi>ſurmize;</hi> and thereon did proceed</l>
                  <l>To <hi>muſe,</hi> as if he had been dead indeed</l>
                  <l>And buried too. From whence, broak in upon me,</l>
                  <l>Such apprehenſions of the <hi>Favours</hi> done me,</l>
                  <l>And of his kindneſſes in my oppreſſions,</l>
                  <l>That, they exacted from me thoſe confeſſions</l>
                  <l>Which in the following pages wil enſue</l>
                  <l>To give, what to his <hi>memory</hi> is due.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dear GOD! if</hi> humane mercy <hi>ſo indears</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t, ſo pretious, if that</hi> Love <hi>appears</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(And ſo obliging) which enjoy'd may be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By</hi> Creatures! <hi>what is that, which flows from thee?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If, little</hi> ſparklings, <hi>may beget a</hi> flame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What may be thought of</hi> that, <hi>from whence they came?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, why from</hi> him <hi>ſhould not my</hi> ſoul <hi>aſcend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To claſp thy</hi> love, <hi>oh my</hi> Eternal Friend!</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who</hi> wert, <hi>and</hi> art, <hi>and wilt</hi> continue <hi>ſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When all the</hi> World <hi>ſhall into</hi> nothing <hi>go!</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some will at <hi>firſt,</hi> perhaps, with prejudice</l>
                  <l>Peruſe, what in this <hi>Poeme I</hi> expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>On this <hi>Occaſion;</hi> judging, that, hereby</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I, ſomewhat</hi> would, beyond the <hi>verity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inſinuate; to make <hi>ſmall things,</hi> appear</l>
                  <l>More in the <hi>ſhow,</hi> then they in <hi>ſubſtance</hi> are.</l>
                  <l>But they ſhall ſee at <hi>laſt,</hi> that, <hi>I</hi> purſue</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Theame</hi> no farther then <hi>I</hi> make it true:</l>
                  <l>And, bear me witnes, ere this hath an end,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I</hi> have done but what becomes a <hi>Friend:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, <hi>real cauſe,</hi> occaſion'd my unreſt:</l>
                  <l>And, that, of <hi>him,</hi> my thoughts are here expreſt,</l>
                  <l>Without <hi>hyperbo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es;</hi> without <hi>deviſing</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or adding, what the World cal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>Poetizing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, <hi>I</hi> rather put upon the <hi>ſcore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leſſe,</hi> then <hi>I</hi> ow his <hi>memory,</hi> then <hi>more.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119976:4"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, to the <hi>matter:</hi> being full of grief,</l>
                  <l>By what my fear had rais'd up to <hi>belief,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſay, within my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> thus began;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weſtrowe,</hi> that noble ſingle hearted man,</l>
                  <l>Whom GOD, had in a time of need beſtown</l>
                  <l>To be my <hi>Friend,</hi> is now no more his <hi>own.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Alas! nor <hi>mine: Weſtrowe,</hi> that heretofore,</l>
                  <l>Was, to the <hi>Widdow, Fatherleſs,</hi> and <hi>poor,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Husband, Friend,</hi> and <hi>Father,</hi> them to feed,</l>
                  <l>To cloath, and harbor, in the time of need.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weſtrowe,</hi> GODS faithfull <hi>Almner;</hi> he, from whom</l>
                  <l>No <hi>needy ſoul,</hi> who for relief did come,</l>
                  <l>Went <hi>empty</hi> (if his <hi>needines</hi> requir'd,</l>
                  <l>Undoubtedly, the ſuccor he deſerv'd)</l>
                  <l>And, then, as GOD doth, he did <hi>alms</hi> beſtow</l>
                  <l>Upon the <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>bad,</hi> on <hi>Friend,</hi> and <hi>Foe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, and when none did <hi>ask,</hi> what he could grant,</l>
                  <l>Sought where to find out thoſe, who ſtood in want:</l>
                  <l>And, often, was directed unto them,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Providence,</hi> in acceptable time.</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Weſtrowe,</hi> now, hath left us to bemoan</l>
                  <l>Our loſſes. For thereby, he can have none,</l>
                  <l>Nor meant us any: But, is gone away</l>
                  <l>That, our <hi>contentment,</hi> he make perfect may</l>
                  <l>By his <hi>well-being,</hi> in a ſafe poſſeſſing,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>portion,</hi> in an <hi>everlaſting Bleſſing:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, we may look off, from <hi>him,</hi> to heed</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Love,</hi> from whom, all <hi>mercies</hi> do proceed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Weſtrowe</hi> is gone, and we remaining have</l>
                  <l>No more of <hi>him,</hi> but what is in his <hi>Grave:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There, now, he reſteth, and exchanged hath</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Life mortifide,</hi> for an <hi>inlivening death.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, him I do behold in <hi>contemplation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So repreſented, by <hi>transfiguration,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As having laid that <hi>earthly vail</hi> aſide</l>
                  <l>(Which from the <hi>World,</hi> his <hi>better parts</hi> did hide)</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119976:4"/>
                  <l>That, I will now diſcloſe them; therefore, ſtay</l>
                  <l>And, know him <hi>Reader,</hi> ere thou go away.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor few, nor mean <hi>Advantages</hi> he had</l>
                  <l>Relating to this <hi>life,</hi> But, theſe were made</l>
                  <l>Of ſmall account, with him; and, uſed ſo,</l>
                  <l>As if with them, he little had to do,</l>
                  <l>Except, for others ſakes: For, he denide</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Himſelf,</hi> to all things, but, <hi>Chriſt crucifide;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, in reſpect of <hi>him,</hi> plac'd thoſe among</l>
                  <l>Such deſpicable things, as <hi>droſſe</hi> and <hi>dung;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He therefore, let them paſs, to be forgot;</l>
                  <l>And, will not mention, what he prized not.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, <hi>living,</hi> walk'd <hi>upright,</hi> in <hi>crooked ways,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, choſe the <hi>beſt part,</hi> in the <hi>worſt of days.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He, <hi>dying,</hi> cheerfully, <hi>himſelf</hi> denide,</l>
                  <l>That (being thereby wholly nudifide</l>
                  <l>From all that was his own), he might be clothd,</l>
                  <l>With what he <hi>lov'd,</hi> inſtead of what he <hi>lothd.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, he that can throw off, ſuch Rags as theſe,</l>
                  <l>Shall find himſelf, exceedingly at eaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How, can I know this, ſome, perhaps, may ſay,</l>
                  <l>If he be dead, and I now far away:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus;</hi> when I ſaw him laſt, I, ſaw him then</l>
                  <l>Himſelf <hi>undreſſing,</hi> from that bane of men</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Self-love,</hi> and <hi>ſelfneſs;</hi> and I know, he never</l>
                  <l>Would fall from his intention, and endevour,</l>
                  <l>Till that were done. For, I was always neer him</l>
                  <l>In <hi>ſpirit,</hi> though, I did not <hi>ſee,</hi> nor <hi>hear</hi> him.</l>
                  <l>We did communicate (when not by <hi>quill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or with our <hi>tongues</hi>) in <hi>ſpirit,</hi> and in <hi>will</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As <hi>Angels</hi> do: yea, many times, when we</l>
                  <l>In <hi>words</hi> and <hi>terms,</hi> appear'd to diſagree,</l>
                  <l>(Becauſe of that defect which is in thoſe)</l>
                  <l>Ev'n then, in <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>ſpirit,</hi> we did cloſe:</l>
                  <l>And, they whom ſuch <hi>experiments</hi> acquaints</l>
                  <l>With that <hi>communion</hi> which belongs to <hi>Saints</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119976:5"/>
                  <l>Do know, that men may credibly aver,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, what they did neither <hi>ſee,</hi> nor <hi>hear:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, worthy my regard it doth not ſeem,</l>
                  <l>What, others, of this <hi>miſtery</hi> ſhall deem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This confidence of <hi>Him,</hi> is but the ſame</l>
                  <l>Which he expreſt of <hi>me,</hi> when laſt I came</l>
                  <l>To <hi>viſit</hi> him; at which time, I receiv'd</l>
                  <l>Aſſurance, of what is of him beleev'd:</l>
                  <l>For, theſe, the <hi>laſt words</hi> were, which from his <hi>tongue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I heard; and, they, from this <hi>occaſion</hi> ſprung.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I told him, that I might be faulty judg'd,</l>
                  <l>(Conſidering how to him I was oblig'd)</l>
                  <l>That, nor by <hi>converſation,</hi> nor by <hi>pen,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> lately had with <hi>him,</hi> (like other men)</l>
                  <l>My <hi>thoughts</hi> communicated; but perſu'd</l>
                  <l>My own <hi>affairs,</hi> as if to be renu'd,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Friendſhip,</hi> needed not thoſe complements</l>
                  <l>VVhich <hi>diſcontinance of reſpect</hi> prevents.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To ſuch effect <hi>I</hi> ſpake; whereto, he gave</l>
                  <l>This anſwer (which I oft repeated have</l>
                  <l>VVith much contentment;) trouble not thy ſelf,</l>
                  <l>VVith needleſs things, we are now paſt the <hi>ſhelf,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That ſhip-wracks <hi>friendſhip.</hi> That, which ſeems <hi>neglect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To others; and begets a <hi>diſ-reſpect,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Secures you more to me, then if you had</l>
                  <l>Left your <hi>affairs</hi> at hazzard; <hi>viſits</hi> made;</l>
                  <l>And added to your <hi>frequent viſitations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Acknowledgments of Debts, and Obligations</l>
                  <l>As others do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>It</hi> would not give me more</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſſurance</hi> of you, then <hi>I</hi> had before.</l>
                  <l>For, my own heart, hath ſo informed me,</l>
                  <l>Of what you are; and of what you ſhall be</l>
                  <l>VVith an aſſurance, ſo undubitable,</l>
                  <l>(And everlaſtingly irrevocable)</l>
                  <l>That, whatſoever ſhall of you be told,</l>
                  <l>(Though we each other never more behold</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:119976:5"/>
                  <l>Nor line comes from you) <hi>I,</hi> ſhall <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>dye,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More confident, of your <hi>ſincerity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, if it were expreſſed every day,</l>
                  <l>By all that <hi>you,</hi> or <hi>other men</hi> could ſay.</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>words</hi> (though mine) give, really, the <hi>ſence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVherein, he did expreſs his <hi>confidence:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this <hi>ſence,</hi> his <hi>laſt words</hi> to me he ſpoke;</l>
                  <l>And, ſo, my <hi>everlaſting leave I</hi> took.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> think, it may inferred be, from hence,</l>
                  <l>Things may be known, beyond the reach of <hi>ſence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVithout <hi>corporall preſence;</hi> and that we</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſome things,</hi> though but part of them we ſee,</l>
                  <l>May know the reſt: He, that doth ſee me <hi>go,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And hear me <hi>ſpeak,</hi> may, without queſtion, know</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I</hi> have <hi>heart,</hi> and <hi>lungs;</hi> although his <hi>eye</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ne'r ſaw them, or the <hi>place</hi> in which they lye:</l>
                  <l>And, he, that knows but what he <hi>hears,</hi> and <hi>ſees,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is from a <hi>beaſt</hi> removed ſo fevv degrees,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I</hi> ſhall mention unto him, in vain</l>
                  <l>VVhat to the <hi>Saints communion</hi> doth pertain.</l>
                  <l>Only to thoſe <hi>I,</hi> therefore vvill proceed,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak, vvho can <hi>beleeve,</hi> as vvell <hi>read:</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To <hi>be,</hi> he rather labor'd, then to <hi>ſeem;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſought his <hi>honor</hi> in <hi>ſelf-diſeſteem.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He vvanted not repute, of being <hi>good,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Save, vvhere his <hi>meaning</hi> vvas <hi>miſunderſtood;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich ſeldom hapned, but, vvhere prepoſſeſſion</l>
                  <l>Gain'd entrance, by a miſ begot <hi>ſuſpition,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And vvhat he ſuffered by it, did produce,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Effects,</hi> vvhich vvere to him of ſome good uſe:</l>
                  <l>And ſuch as gave ſometimes <hi>occaſions,</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>Of that, vvhich <hi>good</hi> to other men vvill do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such, as did knovv him vvell, knevv none to be</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A truer Friend,</hi> or <hi>better man</hi> then <hi>he.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He,</hi> by <hi>youths frailties,</hi> learned to improve</l>
                  <l>In riper years, th'increaſe of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119976:6"/>
                  <l>And, by his <hi>life,</hi> exemplified that,</l>
                  <l>Of which the <hi>Formaliſt,</hi> doth only prate</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His <hi>Charity,</hi> was large; yet, what he did</l>
                  <l>As much as might be, he from others hid.</l>
                  <l>For, often, his <hi>miſdoings,</hi> he would tell,</l>
                  <l>But, ſeldom mention, wherein, he <hi>did well.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He</hi> took more comfort, in a <hi>needfull giving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then pleaſure, in <hi>large benefits</hi> receiving.</l>
                  <l>And (liking not their <hi>thrift,</hi> who do defer</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Almſdeeds,</hi> untill their treaſures uſeleſs are</l>
                  <l>Unto themſelves) he did, by timely <hi>giving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forgiving,</hi> and a ſeaſonable <hi>relieving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shew, he <hi>beleev'd,</hi> that, thereby leave he ſhall,</l>
                  <l>More to <hi>his childe,</hi> then if he leſt him <hi>all.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that, he fear'd, ſhould he not fructifie,</l>
                  <l>(When, in his hungry members, <hi>Chriſt,</hi> paſs'd by)</l>
                  <l>Till, that which may be call'd <hi>his own time,</hi> came,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He,</hi> and the <hi>curſed figtree,</hi> were the ſame.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He,</hi> in his <hi>judgment,</hi> joyned not in one,</l>
                  <l>With ſome good men: But, diſagreed with <hi>none</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So far, as to infringe the <hi>band of peace;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, hinder <hi>Chriſtian charities</hi> increaſe:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, he knew, the <hi>wiſeſt,</hi> here belowe,</l>
                  <l>Know but in <hi>part,</hi> the things they ought to know:</l>
                  <l>And, that, to clear his <hi>ſight,</hi> GOD, now and then,</l>
                  <l>Did leave a <hi>darkneſs</hi> upon other men;</l>
                  <l>Yea, and ſometimes, a <hi>frowardneſs,</hi> to prove</l>
                  <l>And exerciſe, his <hi>patience.</hi> and his <hi>love.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Chriſtian liberty,</hi> he did profeſs,</l>
                  <l>Without allowing of <hi>licentiouſneſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He, labour'd, that, the <hi>Conſcience</hi> might be <hi>free,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>force,</hi> (yea though depravd it ſeem'd to be,)</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, he ſaw more <hi>hypocrites</hi> thereby</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Converts</hi> made; and, that <hi>hypocriſie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is worſe then error; For, it ſeldom <hi>burns,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and, to <hi>GOD,</hi> as rarely <hi>turns.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119976:6"/>
                  <l>Becauſe likewiſe, he was not vvithout fears,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>ſome,</hi> vvho burn'd in zeal, <hi>to weed out tares,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Might <hi>purpoſely,</hi> or <hi>cauſually,</hi> inſtead</l>
                  <l>Of that which they pretended forth to <hi>weed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Either pluck up the <hi>wheat,</hi> or do it hurt,</l>
                  <l>By careleſs treading it, into the durt.</l>
                  <l>For, hardly, can <hi>diſtinguiſhment</hi> be made</l>
                  <l>Twixt <hi>Ray,</hi> and <hi>Wheat,</hi> when they are in the <hi>blade.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Moreover, ſince the <hi>owner</hi> of the <hi>Corn,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Commanded, that ſuch <hi>weeds</hi> ſhould be forborn</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>Harveſt,</hi> to aſſent, he was afraid,</l>
                  <l>That, this <hi>Commandment</hi> ſhould be diſobaid,</l>
                  <l>Leſt, to <hi>himſelf,</hi> he might contract the guilt</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>blood,</hi> that may be innocently ſpilt.</l>
                  <l>And, from this <hi>tendernes,</hi> ſome took <hi>offence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not juſtly given, or ariſing thence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, <hi>he</hi> ſometimes, did put himſelf to trouble,</l>
                  <l>By vainly building, with <hi>wood, ſtraw,</hi> or <hi>ſtubble,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(As all men do) which quite away conſumes</l>
                  <l>To <hi>nothing,</hi> when the <hi>fiery tryall</hi> comes;</l>
                  <l>The loſſe was his, which only did redound</l>
                  <l>To loſſe, of what, was better <hi>loſt,</hi> then <hi>found.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He was but <hi>man;</hi> and <hi>man</hi> at beſt, is <hi>light,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And muſt have <hi>grains</hi> allow'd to make him <hi>weight.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he had <hi>fallings,</hi> and his <hi>humane failings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So he had alſo <hi>riſings,</hi> and <hi>prevailings;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And all GODS Saints have leſſe advantag'd been,</l>
                  <l>By their own <hi>righteouſnes,</hi> then by their <hi>ſin:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, both muſt be diſclaim'd, and they brook worſt,</l>
                  <l>And find it hardeſt, to renounce the <hi>firſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He,</hi> by ſtil cleaving to the true <hi>foundation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And gratious <hi>Author</hi> of our preſervation)</l>
                  <l>Found <hi>himſelf</hi> ſafe, when all thoſe <hi>works</hi> were gone,</l>
                  <l>Which he had vainly builded thereupon.</l>
                  <l>And was well pleas'd to ſee that turn'd to <hi>ſmoke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherein, he, formerly had pleaſure took.</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:119976:7"/>
                  <l>Which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvere it heeded vvell, vvould (ſans all doubt)</l>
                  <l>Conclude thoſe <hi>Quarrels,</hi> which ariſe about</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>ſuperſtructures,</hi> and muſt be denide</l>
                  <l>As uſeles, when by <hi>fire</hi> they ſhall be tride.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To <hi>truth eſſentiall,</hi> he did firm adhear</l>
                  <l>Although ſometimes, in <hi>termes,</hi> he did appear</l>
                  <l>To leave it: And, when thither he retired,</l>
                  <l>Where, he in <hi>quiet privacy,</hi> expired;</l>
                  <l>His <hi>mind,</hi> he ſo compos'd, did ſo confute</l>
                  <l>All <hi>ſelf-miſtakings,</hi> by a <hi>ſelf-diſpute;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſo <hi>examined,</hi> and ſo <hi>repented,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>All,</hi> whereto by miſtakes he had aſſented,</l>
                  <l>Unwarrantably (whether, it related</l>
                  <l>To ought which had been <hi>publickly</hi> debated,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>privatly;</hi> For <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Common-weal</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For GOD or <hi>men.</hi>) And, there, ſo ſetled all</l>
                  <l>His <hi>Intereſts;</hi> that vvith a quiet mind,</l>
                  <l>He did enjoy the <hi>peace,</hi> he ſought to find;</l>
                  <l>And<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unto GOD, a reſignation made,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>will, opinions,</hi> and of all he had:</l>
                  <l>Even of his <hi>ſelfnes;</hi> and therein, found more</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enjoyment,</hi> then, in all the world before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His <hi>body,</hi> was conſumed, by the zeal</l>
                  <l>He bore to GODS <hi>houſe,</hi> and this <hi>Common-weal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And, by foreſeeing, that he might outlive,</l>
                  <l>The honour of that <hi>Repreſentative</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Of which he was a <hi>Member,</hi>) For, when he</l>
                  <l>And <hi>I,</hi> our thoughts confer'd, we might foreſee,</l>
                  <l>That, in a ſhort time (as my <hi>muſe</hi> foretold,</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>moneths</hi> before it came) that happen would</l>
                  <l>Which now is come to paſſe, although thoſe few,</l>
                  <l>Who to the <hi>Publike Intereſt</hi> were true,</l>
                  <l>Had neither <hi>counſel,</hi> nor <hi>endeavour</hi> ſpar'd,</l>
                  <l>To help keep off the <hi>miſchief</hi> that was fear'd.</l>
                  <l>Ere, therefore, <hi>actually</hi> it did enſue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tir'de out,</hi> with vain endeav'rings, he withdrew<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:119976:7"/>
                  <l>A <hi>place</hi> for his <hi>retirement</hi> he had choſe,</l>
                  <l>Near to the Banks of <hi>Thame,</hi> vvhere backvvard flovvs,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Tide</hi> at higheſt, up againſt the ſtream;</l>
                  <l>That, he might neither be too far from them,</l>
                  <l>To vvhom he had <hi>Relations,</hi> nor too nigh</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as might diſturb his <hi>privacy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There, what he could not other waves promote,</l>
                  <l>He ſought to further by a <hi>zealous Vote.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There, <hi>private prayers,</hi> offered he at home,</l>
                  <l>That, GOD himſelf would (for the time to come)</l>
                  <l>Aſſume the <hi>Work,</hi> and call in thoſe thereto</l>
                  <l>Who, might accompliſh, what they could not do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>World,</hi> thus left He, er'e it him forſook:</l>
                  <l>Againſt the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> the <hi>Spirits</hi> part he took;</l>
                  <l>And by their <hi>combatings,</hi> attain'd to have</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> er'e he had a <hi>Grave.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, lo, their long fought <hi>Battel</hi> novv is paſt,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Spirit</hi> triumphs, and the <hi>fleſh,</hi> at laſt</l>
                  <l>By yeelding to be <hi>conquered,</hi> hath vvon,</l>
                  <l>More, then by being <hi>victor,</hi> it had done;</l>
                  <l>And now is lodg'd, in her <hi>withdrawing-room,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To reſt, untill the <hi>tiumph-day</hi> ſhall come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There, from it <hi>labors,</hi> let it therefore, ceaſe;</l>
                  <l>There, let it lye in <hi>hope,</hi> and reſt in <hi>peace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till, to a better <hi>life,</hi> that <hi>Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>we,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rais'd by a ſecond <hi>Reſurrection</hi> be</l>
                  <l>There to appear, where we ſhall fully know</l>
                  <l>What is but darkly, apprehended now:</l>
                  <l>Where, we ſhall ſee the root of all thoſe things,</l>
                  <l>Whence flow our needleſs bitter <hi>Quarrellings;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, where, accordingly we ſhall receive,</l>
                  <l>To what we <hi>acted,</hi> or, as we <hi>beleeve.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Oh! come LORD JESUS come, and fetch us thithes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Gather thy <hi>Saints,</hi> and <hi>choſen-ones</hi> together;</l>
                  <l>And, mean time, in that <hi>Saint</hi> be glorifi'd</l>
                  <l>For whoſe <hi>commemoration I</hi> provide.</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119976:8"/>
                  <l>By <hi>thine,</hi> and their <hi>examples,</hi> who do follow</l>
                  <l>Their ſteps, Oh! ſo inform us, how to hallow</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>hearts,</hi> ſo cleanſe our <hi>hands,</hi> and guide our <hi>feet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, they now gone before, and we may meet.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou,</hi> that art both our <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>way</hi> therto;</l>
                  <l>That <hi>open door,</hi> through which we are to go:</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Fountain</hi> alwayes flowing, to refreſh</l>
                  <l>The thirſting <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the fainting <hi>Fleſh;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Supply unto us, by thy <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What, by our ſelves, and others, we have loſt.</l>
                  <l>O thou! who (being GOD'S <hi>eternal Son,</hi>)</l>
                  <l>To free us, from a <hi>dungeon,</hi> leftſt a <hi>Throne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, underneath his heavy wrath didſt lye</l>
                  <l>Till thou crid'ſt out <hi>Lamaſabakthani.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Heav'nly joyes,</hi> convert our <hi>earthly greef;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Decreaſe our <hi>doubtings,</hi> and increaſe <hi>Beleef;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>carnal love,</hi> improve to <hi>love divine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Till our <hi>Affections</hi> looſe themſelves in thine?</l>
                  <l>Oh! let that <hi>Love,</hi> from whence all <hi>beings</hi> flow,</l>
                  <l>Which made all things <hi>above,</hi> and all <hi>below:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> did firſt ſet them in their way,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Providence,</hi> preſerv'd them to this day,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall hereafter, govern and diſpoſe,</l>
                  <l>That which keeps <hi>Order,</hi> and that, which <hi>miſgoes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh! haſten to perfection! haſten on,</l>
                  <l>The work intended, ere the world begun;</l>
                  <l>And, let that <hi>Glory,</hi> which produce it ſhall,</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>his</hi> (and his alone) that's <hi>ALL</hi> in <hi>ALL.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus, <hi>muſed I,</hi> or, much (if not the ſame,)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To this effect, before the <hi>morning</hi> came.</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>contemplations,</hi> ere I knew him dead,</l>
                  <l>By thinking on my <hi>Friend,</hi> conceiv'd I had,</l>
                  <l>Which afterward, in <hi>words,</hi> thus, up I dreſt;</l>
                  <l>To leave it thereby, vocally expreſt,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>penance,</hi> I was put to, for omitting</l>
                  <l>A duty, my obligements well befitting</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119976:8"/>
                  <l>Then, as the dawning <hi>Light</hi> began to creep</l>
                  <l>About my Chamber, I fell faſt aſleep.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Next day, (no longer meaning to defer</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Viſit,</hi> but till means prepared were)</l>
                  <l>I, meeting with a Friend of his and mine,</l>
                  <l>Informed him, what, I did <hi>predivine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What I had <hi>ſuffered,</hi> what, I have <hi>done,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With what, I had that day reſolv'd upon;</l>
                  <l>And, to prevent it, was aſſur'd by him,</l>
                  <l>That, my <hi>Preſagings,</hi> were no idle dream;</l>
                  <l>For, he was <hi>dead</hi> indeed, and on the morrow</l>
                  <l>To be <hi>interr'd;</hi> which did renew my ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>And, reingage me, further to purſue</l>
                  <l>What, to his pious <hi>Memory</hi> is due.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, there is much behind, as yet unſaid;</l>
                  <l>Which, being truly <hi>known,</hi> and duly <hi>weighd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will add a fairer luſtre to his <hi>Fame;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not without ſome reflectings, to my ſhame,</l>
                  <l>For, leaving him, without a <hi>Valediction,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who was ſo true a <hi>Friend</hi> in my affliction.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Aſſoon therefore, as I have gotten leiſure,</l>
                  <l>What's yet remaining, forth in <hi>Words,</hi> to meaſure</l>
                  <l>Expect it; and in <hi>pawn</hi> thereof, (till I,</l>
                  <l>Shall to your view expoſe it) let this lye;</l>
                  <l>With this enſuing <hi>Epitaph,</hi> till <hi>He</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall honour'd, by a better <hi>muſing</hi> be.</l>
               </lg>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <head>The EPITAPH.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>HIs GRAVE (though he deſired none</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Name,</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> thereupon)</l>
                     <l>Was made below this <hi>Marble ſtone?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And, here, interred, now, <hi>He</hi> lies,</l>
                     <l>To wait CHRISTS coming in the <hi>Skies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At whoſe approach the DEAD ſhall riſe.</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119976:9"/>
                     <l>Yet, ſeek not here, among the DEAD,</l>
                     <l>(On <hi>ſtones,</hi> or <hi>braſs,</hi> or <hi>ſheets of Lead</hi>)</l>
                     <l>What, to his honour may be read:</l>
                     <l>But, if you more of <hi>him,</hi> would hear,</l>
                     <l>Peruſe the <hi>ſheets,</hi> whoſe <hi>Forefronts</hi> bear</l>
                     <l>His NAME inſcribed; and read <hi>him,</hi> there.</l>
                     <l>For though that MONUMENT be built</l>
                     <l>Withou <hi>coſt graving paint,</hi> or <hi>guilt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It ſhall remain, when <hi>this</hi> is ſpilt:</l>
                     <l>Yea, though it hath but <hi>paper wings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It ſhall out laſt, thoſe laſting things,</l>
                     <l>Which, make up <hi>Monuments</hi> for <hi>Kings.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="canto">
               <head>
                  <hi>CANTO</hi> the ſecond.</head>
               <argument>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>After a due</hi> preoccupation,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>It offers to</hi> commemoration,</l>
                     <l>Particulars: <hi>Inſiſts upon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A rarely</hi> memorable-one</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Illuſtrating a</hi> matchles Friend;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, ſo, this Canto hath an end.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe foll'wing <hi>evening,</hi> after I had heard</l>
                  <l>That verifide, whereof I was afeard</l>
                  <l>The <hi>night</hi> before, I, then a freſh inſpir'd,</l>
                  <l>To give my <hi>Muſings</hi> utterance, retir'd.</l>
                  <l>And, that no <hi>interruptions</hi> I might find,</l>
                  <l>Put all my own <hi>concernments,</hi> out of mind.</l>
                  <l>For, he that honeſtly <hi>one work,</hi> would do,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not, the ſame time, be imploy'd on <hi>two.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119976:9"/>
                  <l>But, on the paper, ere I fixt my pen,</l>
                  <l>Such things, as poſſibly by other men</l>
                  <l>Might be objected, queſtion'd, or alleadg'd,</l>
                  <l>To hinder that, wherein I was ingag'd,</l>
                  <l>Ruſh'd in upon me; and, <hi>delaies,</hi> had wrought,</l>
                  <l>Had I not on a ſudden kickt them out;</l>
                  <l>And given ſome of them, (ere they would go;)</l>
                  <l>Areaſonable civell anſwer too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Among the reſt, <hi>One</hi> (vvho ſcarce vvent avvay</l>
                  <l>Well ſatisfide vvith ought that <hi>I</hi> could ſay)</l>
                  <l>Thus queſtion'd me: Art thou become ſo vain,</l>
                  <l>To think, by <hi>charmes,</hi> and <hi>words</hi> to raiſe again</l>
                  <l>The <hi>dead</hi> to <hi>life;</hi> or, to preſerve the <hi>Name</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>freinds deceaſed,</hi> by ſurviving <hi>Fame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Among this <hi>Generation,</hi> wherein none</l>
                  <l>Or few, regard what ſhall be <hi>ſaid,</hi> or <hi>done,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To that effect? Canſt thou have hope to bring</l>
                  <l>By <hi>poeſie</hi> (which an <hi>unhallowed thing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is now accounted) any due reſpect</l>
                  <l>To <hi>him,</hi> whoſe memory thou doſt affect?</l>
                  <l>Or, think that thou maiſt dignifie his <hi>Herſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By ſuch a deſpicable thing, as <hi>verſe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Canſt thou hope this, when he that <hi>verſifies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seems but a coyner, of facetious <hi>Lies?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When lovers of the <hi>muſes,</hi> are ſo ſcanty,</l>
                  <l>That, there are hardly two, in five times twenty,</l>
                  <l>Who, if thy <hi>Poem</hi> ſerious be, will heed it;</l>
                  <l>Or, (if they will) that have the wit to read it,</l>
                  <l>More gracefully, then if an <hi>Aſſe</hi> ſhould play</l>
                  <l>Upon a <hi>Harp,</hi> or to the <hi>Viol</hi> bray?</l>
                  <l>For, neither heeding <hi>accents, points,</hi> or <hi>time,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They, only make a clinking on the <hi>Rime.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More harſhly grating on juditious ears,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>ſcraping trenchers,</hi> which none gladly hears?</l>
                  <l>And, what, of all thy <hi>muſings,</hi> have th'effects</l>
                  <l>Been hitherto, but <hi>troubles,</hi> and <hi>neglects?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119976:10"/>
                  <l>This being urg'd, I, thereto made reply</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus, in my ſelf: Admit all this, quoth <hi>I:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mo <hi>wiſeman</hi> fears to do, what ſhould be done</l>
                  <l>Through dread of that which may miſ-fall thereon:</l>
                  <l>Nor, ſo much cares, what may thereof be thought,</l>
                  <l>As to be always doing, as he ought.</l>
                  <l>It is the <hi>Muſes</hi> duty, to be there</l>
                  <l>Moſt <hi>active,</hi> where, moſt <hi>Difficulties</hi> are;</l>
                  <l>And, moſt couragiouſly, there to advance</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Standards,</hi> where appears moſt <hi>Ignorance;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That to <hi>ſucceeding Ages</hi> they may leave</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things, which <hi>preſent times,</hi> will not receive.</l>
                  <l>It is a <hi>portion,</hi> whereto they were born</l>
                  <l>To be expoſed to contempt and ſcorn;</l>
                  <l>And, tis their <hi>honour,</hi> to have wiſely dar'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſt things,</hi> for which, the world gives no reward.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Though <hi>Poets</hi> are deſpis'd, and, will yet more</l>
                  <l>Contemned be, (and thruſt behind the doore)</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Ignorance</hi> gets ground; and, as the <hi>Baſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall riſe to ſit in honourable place;</l>
                  <l>There was a time, when <hi>Princes</hi> did contend</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Poetry,</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi> to befriend;</l>
                  <l>And, when the <hi>one</hi> ſhall conſecrate his <hi>Muſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>True <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Virtue</hi> to infuſe;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>men in power,</hi> by <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> maintain</l>
                  <l>Their dignity, it ſhall be ſo again.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Muſes,</hi> in times paſt, ſo awfull were</l>
                  <l>That, they made <hi>Kings</hi> to fawn, and <hi>Tyrants</hi> fear.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Vulger,</hi> they made <hi>Hero's; Hero's GODS:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Drew <hi>Trees</hi> and <hi>Beaſts,</hi> out of the ſalvage woods,</l>
                  <l>To follow them: That is, they drew together</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Blockiſh</hi> and <hi>bruitiſh men</hi> (as rude as either</l>
                  <l>Wild <hi>Plants,</hi> or <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and them allur'd unto</l>
                  <l>What <hi>reaſonable creatures</hi> ought to do.</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Charm</hi> threw down the <hi>vicious</hi> to that hell,</l>
                  <l>Where everlaſting <hi>Infamy</hi> doth dwell:</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119976:10"/>
                  <l>Raiſd up the <hi>well deſervers</hi> from the <hi>Grave,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>life</hi> of <hi>never dying fame</hi> to have,</l>
                  <l>Yea, by their <hi>charms</hi> they have expel'd the <hi>devill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The furious, and the <hi>melancholy evill.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, not alone in former Generations,</l>
                  <l>Among the learned, and moſt <hi>civill Nations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had Poeſie eſteem, and good effects,</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of <hi>envy, malice,</hi> and <hi>neglects.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, alſo, here, and lately ſome have lived</l>
                  <l>Who, by their <hi>muſings,</hi> honor have received.</l>
                  <l>And been enabled, by their inſpirations,</l>
                  <l>To vindicate the <hi>Muſes</hi> reputations.</l>
                  <l>Yea, (in his meaſure) ev'n the barbarous <hi>Bard,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is of his, <hi>people,</hi> ſo belov'd, or fear'd;</l>
                  <l>That, whom ſoere he pleaſes (by his <hi>rimes</hi>)</l>
                  <l>He makes to be the <hi>minion</hi> of the times</l>
                  <l>Within his <hi>Orb:</hi> And, they among us here,</l>
                  <l>Who of this <hi>faculty</hi> the <hi>maſters</hi> are</l>
                  <l>(As to the language) can th'<hi>affections</hi> raiſe,</l>
                  <l>And move the Readers <hi>paſſions</hi> various wayes,</l>
                  <l>By their <hi>compoſures;</hi> though they do abuſe</l>
                  <l>His gift, who did that <hi>faculty</hi> infuſe;</l>
                  <l>As I my ſelf have done, till he that gave it,</l>
                  <l>Inform'd me better, to what end <hi>I</hi> have it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then, why, with confidency may not I,</l>
                  <l>Hope by the help of ſacred <hi>poeſie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So to embalm my Friend, by that <hi>perfume</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which fluently will by extraction come</l>
                  <l>From his own <hi>vertues</hi>) that, a ſweet breath'd <hi>fame,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Disfuſed from the <hi>Orders</hi> of his <hi>Name,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May draw ſome after him? and make them grow</l>
                  <l>In love, with what doth from thoſe <hi>Orders</hi> flow?</l>
                  <l>And, thereby wooe them to an imitation</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>him,</hi> and to a virtuous emulation?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If <hi>David,</hi> in an <hi>fun'rall ſong</hi> preſerved,</l>
                  <l>The memory of that, which well deſerved,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119976:11"/>
                  <l>In wicked <hi>Saul</hi> his foe; why may not I</l>
                  <l>Seek to preſerve a good mans memory?</l>
                  <l>Why may not <hi>I</hi> with warranty commend</l>
                  <l>The matchles love of my deceaſed <hi>Friend?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why may not I, as fully as I can</l>
                  <l>Illuſtrate my beloved <hi>Jonathan?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If, alſo, they, whoſe <hi>poeſie</hi> affords</l>
                  <l>Little ſave empty ſhews, and ſwelling words,</l>
                  <l>Forc'd <hi>Metaphors,</hi> and frothy <hi>ſtrains of wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which on the <hi>Jancy,</hi> ticklings do beget)</l>
                  <l>Peruſed are with ſome effect that's good,</l>
                  <l>And, are moſt pleaſing, when leaſt underſtood)</l>
                  <l>Why may not I, be read by <hi>two,</hi> or <hi>three,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With more advantage both to <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then, by a <hi>thouſand,</hi> that are pleas'd with <hi>chaff,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, at my plain expreſſions jeer, and laugh.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Why may not <hi>I,</hi> who have advantages,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>real merits</hi> (which helps, theſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Impoſtures</hi> had not) <hi>trophies</hi> hope to Rear</l>
                  <l>That ſhall more laſting, and more fair appear</l>
                  <l>Then ſuch as they build, who <hi>compoſures</hi> fain</l>
                  <l>Out of the durty notions of their <hi>brain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, from the <hi>vapours,</hi> that <hi>ſtrong drink</hi> infuſes,</l>
                  <l>To dignifie the ſubject of their <hi>mufes?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Why may not I, this faculty imploy,</l>
                  <l>To build up that, which others do deſtroy,</l>
                  <l>By their abuſing it? and, hope thereby</l>
                  <l>So to repreeve it from that <hi>Obliquie.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which now it ſuffers, that, the <hi>beſt of men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May fall in love with poeſie agen,</l>
                  <l>And, not (as now they do) avert their eyes,</l>
                  <l>As if aſham'd of him that <hi>verſifies?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, this is part, wherto my <hi>Poems</hi> tend</l>
                  <l>Though, peradventure, I may miſs my end.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Let it not therefore, ſeem a prophanation</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Piety,</hi> unto this <hi>Generation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:119976:11"/>
                  <l>That, I adventure to redeem from blame</l>
                  <l>The <hi>gift,</hi> by ſome employed to their ſhame;</l>
                  <l>Since, it was firſt confer'd on each <hi>receiver,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To raiſe up his own <hi>ſpirit,</hi> to the <hi>giver:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, then, to rouſe up other mens affections,</l>
                  <l>From carnal, popular, and vain dejections?</l>
                  <l>Or that, to take my <hi>Reader,</hi> by the ear,</l>
                  <l>I lay among my <hi>verſes.</hi> here and there,</l>
                  <l>Some books, with <hi>reaſon</hi> baited, which, ſometime,</l>
                  <l>Doth eatch thoſe who expected nought but <hi>rime.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Nor, let this (though a long <hi>preoccupation</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Seem to be needleſs, or a vain digreſſion;</l>
                  <l>For, though it nothing <hi>adds,</hi> to my <hi>intents,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The taking <hi>ſomwhat from them,</hi> it prevents;</l>
                  <l>Which being done, ile now proceed to that</l>
                  <l>Wherof, I purpoſe, further to relate.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>ſubject</hi> of my <hi>Muſings,</hi> being large</l>
                  <l>Tis not within my graſpings, to diſcharge</l>
                  <l>What's thereto due; nor can it be confin'd,</l>
                  <l>Within that <hi>compaſſe,</hi> which I have deſign'd.</l>
                  <l>To tell you therefore, fully, <hi>what he was,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>what he was not,</hi> would ſo far ſurpaſſe,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>limit,</hi> that I only muſt expreſſe</l>
                  <l>So much as may enable you to gueſſe</l>
                  <l>At what remains untold, (though it be more</l>
                  <l>Then here enſues, or hath been ſaid before)</l>
                  <l>And that I may, his <hi>inſide</hi> lay to view</l>
                  <l>Which I much better, then his outſide knew.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He was a <hi>man,</hi> indowed with no leſſe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>piety,</hi> then <hi>moral Righteouſnes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And in the practiſing of both, ſo harty</l>
                  <l>That, to the <hi>honeſt,</hi> and the <hi>god'y party;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(As call'd ſome are) he brought a ſupplement,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>reall worth,</hi> as well as <hi>Ornament:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:119976:12"/>
                  <l>And aim'd at that reward, for which he ran,</l>
                  <l>Not in the <hi>outward,</hi> but the <hi>inward-man.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From <hi>youths extravagancies,</hi> which, (as he</l>
                  <l>Hath oft confeſſed) he once thought to be</l>
                  <l>Th'accompliſhments of <hi>Gentry,</hi> without which</l>
                  <l>They had in vain, been <hi>nobly born,</hi> or <hi>rich,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From theſe (ev'n when he moſt indanger'd ſeem'd)</l>
                  <l>He was by GODS <hi>eſpeciall grace</hi> redeemd,</l>
                  <l>(And brought off, by his providentiall hand)</l>
                  <l>In ſeaſonable time; even as a <hi>brand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Snatchd from the <hi>fire.</hi> For, thoſe commodious <hi>places,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prepared for the <hi>Muſes,</hi> and the <hi>Grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To coinhabite in, for education,</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>youth</hi> in knowledge; and to keep this <hi>Nation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>Barbariſme;</hi> Places, were become</l>
                  <l>So fraught with <hi>Vices,</hi> and ſo perilſome,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>hody,</hi> that, he was almoſt</l>
                  <l>By <hi>ill examples,</hi> and <hi>lewd conſorts,</hi> loſt.</l>
                  <l>For which, a threatning <hi>vengeance</hi> hangeth over</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>Seats,</hi> that will admit of no <hi>Remover</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of what is menaced, till their <hi>Foundation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is rooted up, or ſaved by <hi>purgation.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With what <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>varications,</hi> he, was there</l>
                  <l>Impoyſon'd, and what <hi>principles</hi> they were</l>
                  <l>Whereby he was indangerd, he to us</l>
                  <l>Rendr'd as banefull, and ridiculous</l>
                  <l>As words could make them; that, it might advance</l>
                  <l>GOD'S <hi>grace</hi> vouchſafd, for his deliverance;</l>
                  <l>And make them uſeful, unto thoſe who heard</l>
                  <l>What he was ſaved from, and what vvas fear'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He was among the firſt, whoſe <hi>knowing zeal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Flamd our, to vindicate this <hi>Common-weal</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From <hi>thraldom</hi> and <hi>oppreſſion;</hi> thereto moved</l>
                  <l>In <hi>conſcience,</hi> and by <hi>principles</hi> approved.</l>
                  <l>Not ſtirred up, by <hi>factious diſcontent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>raſhneſs, want,</hi> or by malevolent</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119976:12"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Affections,</hi> or <hi>Deſigns;</hi> though not without</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>counterpleas,</hi> in vvhat he went about:</l>
                  <l>For, in immergencies, which do relate</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To private conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Affairs of State,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The wiſeſt man, his <hi>reſolution</hi> brings</l>
                  <l>To ſettlement, by various combatings.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With <hi>him,</hi> thus far'd it: Then he to withſtand</l>
                  <l>The <hi>publick Fo,</hi> was honor'd with <hi>Command;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wherein, he ventur'd not his <hi>life</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>Without that profit, which by many a one</l>
                  <l>Was aim'd at, and enjoy'd) but <hi>lent,</hi> and <hi>give,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, waſted his <hi>Eſtate,</hi> to gard, and ſave</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Publique Intereſt,</hi> without a <hi>prayre</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Exhibited, or <hi>temporall repair.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Unſought for, (as I verily beleeve)</l>
                  <l>He, afterward, the honor did receive</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſupream truſt;</hi> and, without cauſe of blame,</l>
                  <l>According to his powre, diſcharg'd the ſame;</l>
                  <l>The ſpeaking, of no needfull truth forbearing;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>powre,</hi> or <hi>preſence,</hi> of no perſon fearing;</l>
                  <l>Swaid nor by <hi>hatred,</hi> neither by <hi>affection,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To others; nor by that which ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> reflection</l>
                  <l>Upon himſelf; But, freely ſaid his mind,</l>
                  <l>And conſcience, as he did occaſions find,</l>
                  <l>In whatſoever matter was debated;</l>
                  <l>Whether the thing propos'd, to <hi>GOD</hi> related,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Common-wealth:</hi> if they who preſent were,</l>
                  <l>(As I beleeve they did) the truth aver.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, if it ſo did happen that, ſometime</l>
                  <l>A <hi>tender pity,</hi> did prevail with him</l>
                  <l>To plead for <hi>mercy,</hi> on behalf of ſome</l>
                  <l>Made liable, by <hi>law</hi> unto the doom</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>mulct,</hi> or <hi>death;</hi> the ſame he never preſt</l>
                  <l>Ought further, then the <hi>Publique Intereſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith ſafety might allow it: And altho,</l>
                  <l>He felt what other men are moov'd unto.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:119976:13"/>
                  <l>By <hi>naturall Affections,</hi> he did ſtill</l>
                  <l>Conform his <hi>Judgment,</hi> and confine his <hi>will</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To <hi>Juſtice:</hi> And, this, rather doth increaſe</l>
                  <l>His honour, then appear to make it leſs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, though the <hi>Author,</hi> of the <hi>Hiſtory</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Independents,</hi> hath injuriouſly</l>
                  <l>(Among his other Leazings) added him</l>
                  <l>Unto his lying <hi>Catalogue,</hi> of them.</l>
                  <l>Who, to the damage of the <hi>Common-weal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By their <hi>Commands, Gifts, Offices,</hi> or <hi>ſpoil,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Inriched, and aloft advanced be.</l>
                  <l>From <hi>poore eſtates,</hi> and from a <hi>low degree;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>On him, that ſticks not; but, reflects diſgrace</l>
                  <l>Apparently, upon that <hi>Liers</hi> face.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, to all thoſe, who knew him, tis well known,</l>
                  <l>That, with a large eſtate, by birth his own,</l>
                  <l>He was indow'd. His <hi>Mother,</hi> yet, in <hi>Kent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Survive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; a <hi>Lady,</hi> rarely eminent</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Charity,</hi> and for a <hi>open doore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſuch as are in miſery, and poore.</l>
                  <l>And, as he no way needed to inlarge</l>
                  <l>His <hi>portion,</hi> or the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> to charge</l>
                  <l>By ſuch <hi>ſupplies,</hi> as others have deſired</l>
                  <l>(And often <hi>ſurreptitiouſly</hi> acquired)</l>
                  <l>So, he was all his life, ſo far from craving,</l>
                  <l>From wiſhing, from receiving, and from having</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gift, place,</hi> or <hi>office,</hi> whereby he might add</l>
                  <l>An augmentation, unto what he had,</l>
                  <l>That, many vvhom the <hi>Common miſeries</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had begger'd, and vvhoſe <hi>pub iek ſervices,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>wants</hi> he ſavv neglected, he reliev'd</l>
                  <l>Out of his ovvn <hi>eſtate;</hi> and them repriev'd</l>
                  <l>From ruining, vvhen <hi>helper</hi> they had none:</l>
                  <l>Among vvhich number, <hi>I my ſelf,</hi> vvas <hi>one.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, that, vvhich in this kind he lent or gave</l>
                  <l>Was meant (as <hi>I</hi> beleeve) as vvell to ſave</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119976:13"/>
                  <l>The <hi>Nations</hi> honour, as to do a deed</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſimple Charity,</hi> in time of need:</l>
                  <l>For, he preferr'd, the <hi>Publick Faith</hi> before</l>
                  <l>His <hi>private Credit;</hi> and, did ſo abhor</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Avarice,</hi> vvho by a mutual <hi>Giving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Forgiving,</hi> and <hi>unſeaſonably relieving,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obſtructed thoſe <hi>performances,</hi> vvhereby</l>
                  <l>Our deep <hi>Ingagements</hi> did neglected lye:</l>
                  <l>That, to prevent it, he thought fit to ſcatter</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> portion of his bread upon the <hi>water</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leſt after <hi>private miſeries,</hi> things vvorſe</l>
                  <l>Enſude; a <hi>nationall,</hi> a <hi>publick curſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then, thoſe large <hi>Legacies,</hi> vvhich he in death</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Charitable uſes,</hi> did bequeath,</l>
                  <l>(Conſider'd, vvith his frequent bounteous giving,</l>
                  <l>To ſuch as vvere diſtreſt vvhil'ſt he vvas living.)</l>
                  <l>Do make it, vvithout queſtion evident</l>
                  <l>That he, both had enough, and ſuch content</l>
                  <l>With vvhat he had, that, he upon his ſcore</l>
                  <l>Leaves nothing, that ſhall make his Children poor</l>
                  <l>As they vvill do, vvho <hi>gave</hi> and <hi>took</hi> the bread,</l>
                  <l>Wherevvith the <hi>Fatherleſs</hi> ſhould have been fed;</l>
                  <l>And, have, vvith vvhat their <hi>Servants</hi> blood did buy,</l>
                  <l>Inlarg'd their <hi>Fields,</hi> and rais'd their <hi>houſes</hi> high.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, <hi>I</hi> to little purpoſe thus go on</l>
                  <l>To ſet my <hi>Candle</hi> up before the <hi>Sun.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They who had eyes to ſee it did behold,</l>
                  <l>And knew as much before, as I have told.</l>
                  <l>They, who by wilfulnes, <hi>dark-ſighted</hi> be</l>
                  <l>Set up what <hi>light</hi> we can, will never ſee.</l>
                  <l>Now, ſome of you, (it may be) will ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>That my <hi>conjectures</hi> only, <hi>I</hi> diſcloſe;</l>
                  <l>Or that a knowledge of ſuch things <hi>I</hi> fain</l>
                  <l>Which to his <hi>private actings</hi> do pertain;</l>
                  <l>Or, take them up on <hi>Truſt. If,</hi> ſo, they think,</l>
                  <l>So, let it be; <hi>I</hi> will not ſtrive to ſink</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119976:14"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A milſtone in a ſhallow diſh of water;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or ſeek to fill a <hi>viol,</hi> with ſuch matter,</l>
                  <l>As it admits not. Things, vvhich muſt be known</l>
                  <l>As well by <hi>others eyes,</hi> as by my own</l>
                  <l>To make them certain; Ile no further mention,</l>
                  <l>Without proof it ſeem a <hi>ſelf invention</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, which hath paſſed 'tvvixt us tvvo alone;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe things, vvhereof my knovvledg can by none</l>
                  <l>Be doubted of) to mind <hi>I</hi> vvill recall;</l>
                  <l>And, out of many, bring forth <hi>one</hi> for <hi>all;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One, that ſhall ſet forth his <hi>deſerving</hi> more</l>
                  <l>Then all that <hi>I</hi> have mentioned before;</l>
                  <l>(At leſt according to that excellence</l>
                  <l>Which ſuits a <hi>ſenſuall Intelligence</hi>)</l>
                  <l>And, when vvith that <hi>expreſſion I</hi> have done,</l>
                  <l>Ile rather leave it to be thought upon,</l>
                  <l>Then imitated; till <hi>ſelf-love</hi> begins</l>
                  <l>To looſe that ground, vvhich hitherto it vvins.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, that is really a <hi>faithfull friend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath that, vvhich doth vvithin it comprehend</l>
                  <l>All <hi>morall vertues;</hi> yea, and, therevvith too</l>
                  <l>That <hi>charity,</hi> vvhich from true <hi>Faith</hi> doth flovv:</l>
                  <l>For, ſuch a perſon cannot be alone</l>
                  <l>(In being ſo) a <hi>faithfull friend</hi> to <hi>ONE;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But alſo to all others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, extend;</l>
                  <l>His love to all GODS creatures, as his friends<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, doubtles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> far above all thoſe, to <hi>him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, for himſelf alone created them.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>vertue</hi> therefore, doth on men confer</l>
                  <l>The higheſt excellence they can have here;</l>
                  <l>And, this rare <hi>vertue,</hi> (vvhereof, <hi>I,</hi> the Sound</l>
                  <l>Had vainly heard before) in him, <hi>I</hi> found</l>
                  <l>And thereof, ſuch experiment vvill give</l>
                  <l>That, you ſhall think of him, as <hi>I</hi> beleeve;</l>
                  <l>And that in <hi>charity,</hi> he did out go</l>
                  <l>Moſt men, vvho thereof, make the greateſt <hi>ſhow.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:119976:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>That, you may know him; whom I knew ſo well,</l>
                  <l>My means of knowing him, thus, firſt ile tell.</l>
                  <l>The late inteſtine <hi>Wars,</hi> which with a <hi>flood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of miſeries, and with a ſea of <hi>blood</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ore flow'd theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> like a raging <hi>torrent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which bears dovvn all vvith an impetuous current,)</l>
                  <l>Brake in, ev'n at firſt riſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vvhere then lay</l>
                  <l>My chief Eſtate, and ſvvept it all avvay;</l>
                  <l>That, little thereof, vvhich elſevvhere vvas left,</l>
                  <l>Was alſo, by th' <hi>Oppreſſors</hi> hand bereft,</l>
                  <l>Save only ſome ſmall part of my Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>Conſiſting in <hi>rings, houſholdſtuff,</hi> and <hi>plate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which being portable, preſerved vvere,</l>
                  <l>Or got together, by my future care,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>That, vvhich expos'd my <hi>portion</hi> to the raging,</l>
                  <l>Of my <hi>deſtroyers,</hi> vvas, a free ingaging</l>
                  <l>Againſt the <hi>common foe:</hi> And, they, vvith vvhom</l>
                  <l>I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the <hi>Publique<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> did ingag'd become,</l>
                  <l>Gave me the <hi>Publique Faith,</hi> that vvhat <hi>I</hi> loſt</l>
                  <l>Should be repaired at the <hi>publique coſt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that my Children, ſhould be look'd upon</l>
                  <l>VVith favour, and regard, vvhen <hi>I</hi> vvas gone.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By theſe incouragements <hi>I</hi> did purſue</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſervices,</hi> untill <hi>I</hi> neither knevv</l>
                  <l>Which way my <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſent wants,</hi> might have ſupply,</l>
                  <l>Or whereon, for the <hi>future</hi> to rely;</l>
                  <l>And then, perforce, retreated for recruit,</l>
                  <l>To proſecute the <hi>Cauſe</hi> with freſh purſuit:</l>
                  <l>VVhereof <hi>I</hi> got ſome few effects in <hi>ſhow,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich in the <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> prov'd not to be ſo.</l>
                  <l>But rather brought, much greater miſchiefs on me,</l>
                  <l>Then all my open <hi>enemies</hi> had done me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, ſome vvho had but fainedly pretended,</l>
                  <l>To that, vvhich <hi>I</hi> had ſeriouſly defended;</l>
                  <l>Perceiving, me, preparing to diſcloſe</l>
                  <l>Their falſhood, did become my open Foes;</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119976:15"/>
                  <l>And through their Complices (who by the hand</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Providence</hi> were weeded from the Land,</l>
                  <l>Soon after) they ſo wrought, that <hi>Innocence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> were judged an offence,</l>
                  <l>Maugre apparent proofs and demonſtrations</l>
                  <l>Yet extant, by their own examinations:</l>
                  <l>So, I was finde, confinde, and on my head</l>
                  <l>That cenſure lay'd, which they had merited</l>
                  <l>With ſeven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fold more; and for my ſervice paſt</l>
                  <l>Into diſgrace, was innocently caſt,</l>
                  <l>With nothing for ſubſiſtance, but, that poore</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Houſe-furniture,</hi> which was within my doore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To add more burthen to thoſe heavy <hi>weights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And drive me, thereby, into greater <hi>ſtreights;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My <hi>Friends,</hi> and my <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> then began</l>
                  <l>To look upon me as a <hi>faulty man</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who had deceiv'd their hope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo that, if they</l>
                  <l>Who (though too few to help me) day by day</l>
                  <l>Were at my trial, had not ſeen and heard</l>
                  <l>Th'injuſtice done me, and the ſame declar'd;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> had, in likelihood, ere this day, ended</l>
                  <l>My life in want; diſgrac'd, and unbefriended.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, as my <hi>Friends</hi> fell off, my <hi>Foes</hi> fell on</l>
                  <l>With freſh purſute of what they had begun,</l>
                  <l>And<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had not <hi>GOD</hi> in an unlook'd for houre</l>
                  <l>Deprived them of their abuſed <hi>powre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They had deſtroy'd me quite. But, <hi>I,</hi> at laſt</l>
                  <l>Eſcap'd; and they into the pit were caſt.</l>
                  <l>Mean while, they inſolently domineer'd,</l>
                  <l>Made <hi>ſongs</hi> and <hi>pamphlets</hi> on me; ſcoft and jeer'd,</l>
                  <l>And had ſo villifide my Reputation</l>
                  <l>To thoſe who repreſented, then, this <hi>Nation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, of <hi>four thouſand pounds</hi> (to which account</l>
                  <l>My <hi>due</hi> (prov'd fully) truly did amount)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> could not get one penny for relief</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>me,</hi> or <hi>mine,</hi> to mittigate our grief;</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:119976:15"/>
                  <l>Though, I had forced <hi>words</hi> into their ears,</l>
                  <l>Which from <hi>by-ſtanders,</hi> oft, extracted tears;</l>
                  <l>And, to compaſſion, might that <hi>Judg</hi> have wan</l>
                  <l>Who neither feared GOD, nor car'd for <hi>man.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To add yet further, to my great <hi>afflictions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>GOD, with a <hi>ſicknes,</hi> (ſpreading forth infections)</l>
                  <l>Viſits my houſe, and drove all thoſe from thence,</l>
                  <l>Who were ſome comfort in my <hi>indigence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, being ſhut up, and excluded from</l>
                  <l>All other <hi>helpers, I,</hi> to him might come.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>children</hi> were all ſick of that diſeaſe;</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſingle keeper,</hi> to her little eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Was their <hi>ſad Mother,</hi> whilſt (as ſad as ſhe)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> ſought, whereby they might ſupported be.</l>
                  <l>And we, who ſerved were, a while before</l>
                  <l>With ſixteen <hi>houſhold ſervants,</hi> (ſometimes more)</l>
                  <l>Had then, but one Boy (who, ſick alſo lay)</l>
                  <l>And one <hi>poor woman,</hi> hired by the day.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To pay, and feed thoſe, <hi>I</hi> my plate had ſold:</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Wife,</hi> the ſilver, and the lace of gold</l>
                  <l>Which lately trim'd her <hi>Garm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nts,</hi> ript away;</l>
                  <l>To buy things needfull, for the preſent day:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Her Ornaments</hi> ſhe chang'd for <hi>bread,</hi> to eat:</l>
                  <l>Then, ſold the diſhes, which did hold our meat:</l>
                  <l>And laſt of all, our higheſt valued things,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>pretious ſtones,</hi> the <hi>jewels,</hi> and the <hi>rings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To us, from <hi>honorable Perſons</hi> ſent,</l>
                  <l>As tokens of reſpect (the ſame way went.</l>
                  <l>And what was left, ill ſpar'd though it could be)</l>
                  <l>To follow, for ought <hi>I</hi> then could ſee.</l>
                  <l>Only this hope remain'd, that <hi>GOD</hi> had ſent</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſicknes,</hi> which by <hi>death,</hi> would wants prevent;</l>
                  <l>Or, give us by his own hand, ſome <hi>repair:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, of his <hi>love,</hi> I, never ſhall deſpair.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>In this good hope, the <hi>Worlds</hi> neglect <hi>I</hi> ſcorn'd,</l>
                  <l>And my <hi>petitions,</hi> into prayers turn'd,</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:119976:16"/>
                  <l>Directed unto him; who only knew</l>
                  <l>My wants, and what was likely to enſue.</l>
                  <l>But, he likewiſe, to anſwer me delaid;</l>
                  <l>And for a while ſeem'd deaf to what I pray'd:</l>
                  <l>Yet knowing not, what els remain'd to do,</l>
                  <l>Or whether, or to whom, for help to go;</l>
                  <l>Nor caring (if GOD left me) for <hi>ſupplies</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From other hands; <hi>I</hi> ſtill renew'd my cries</l>
                  <l>To him alone, and ſuddenly was cheer'd</l>
                  <l>With ſomewhat, which to <hi>ſence</hi> no where appear'd,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, as a <hi>Loves,</hi> thinking (in a dream)</l>
                  <l>He hears his <hi>beſt Be oued</hi> calling him,</l>
                  <l>Starts up in haſt, and runneth out to meet</l>
                  <l>The <hi>voice</hi> that cals him, ere he find his <hi>feet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And goes he knovvs not whether: So, with me</l>
                  <l>It far'd, who (hoping not deceiv'd to be)</l>
                  <l>Walk'd forth to ſee, if <hi>providence divine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would bring to <hi>ſight,</hi> or <hi>mind,</hi> ſome Friend of mine,</l>
                  <l>Or his, from whom, <hi>I</hi> might that ayd receive</l>
                  <l>Which to obtain from GOD, <hi>I</hi> did beleeve.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, mark his goodnes, Oh! all you that read it</l>
                  <l>So mark it, and with ſeriouſnes ſo heed it</l>
                  <l>That; (if <hi>I</hi> ſhould forget it) you may be</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Remembrancers,</hi> hereafter unto me</l>
                  <l>As <hi>I</hi> have been to you, in former time,</l>
                  <l>Of what concerns this Nation, and this <hi>Clime.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In this <hi>diſtreſſe,</hi> he, meets me, of whom here</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> am diſcourſing; And with pleaſing chear</l>
                  <l>Salutes me thus: Amid thy troubles now</l>
                  <l>How is it with thee <hi>George?</hi> how fareſt thou?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> anſwer'd, <hi>SIR, I</hi> live, though <hi>I</hi> am poore;</l>
                  <l>And, of my <hi>welfare,</hi> cannot ſay much more.</l>
                  <l>Take heart ſaid he; Theſe dayes will have an end,</l>
                  <l>And future times will better thee befriend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſought thee at thy houſe, not with intent</l>
                  <l>To trifle out an hour in <hi>complement</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119976:16"/>
                  <l>But, lovingly brought thither, by a fear</l>
                  <l>Leſt more lay on thee, then thou well mightſt bear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, thy <hi>Petitions</hi> I, have heard, and ſeen,</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe tranſactions I have witnes been,</l>
                  <l>Whereby thou, wert oppreſſed; and wherein</l>
                  <l>Thy Country hath no leſſe abuſed been.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> alſo publickly have heard debated</l>
                  <l>Thy claims, and when they were allow'd, and ſtated;</l>
                  <l>Saw what was juſtly, or unjuſtly done;</l>
                  <l>And am aſſured GOD will look thereon</l>
                  <l>Yea, <hi>I</hi> have ſo well heeded what thou haſt</l>
                  <l>Both lately and in former time expreſt</l>
                  <l>For <hi>GOD,</hi> and alſo for thy Countries ſake,</l>
                  <l>Whereof enſuing times will notice take</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I,</hi> my ſelf to be obliged, thought</l>
                  <l>To ſeek thy welfare; and from GOD have brought</l>
                  <l>This <hi>token of his love<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> thus having ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Juſt twenty pounds into my hand he laid</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>currant gold;</hi> whereat (as one amaz'd)</l>
                  <l>On him with overflowing eyes <hi>I</hi> gaz'd;</l>
                  <l>Not able, for the preſent, to afford</l>
                  <l>The retribution of one <hi>thankfull word.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, out of me, my <hi>heart</hi> away was gone</l>
                  <l>To GOD, who made him do, what he had done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, after <hi>recollection, SIR,</hi> ſaid <hi>I,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat hath mov'd you, to this <hi>charity</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will doubtleſly with intereſt repay</l>
                  <l>What you have miniſtred to me this day;</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>GOD</hi> himſelf alone, and none but he</l>
                  <l>(Who knows in what diſtreſſes all men be)</l>
                  <l>Could, you, to me ſo timely have directed</l>
                  <l>Oppreſt with wants, and of all friends neglected</l>
                  <l>Or, ſo inlarg'd your heart, to bring relief</l>
                  <l>Proportionable to my preſent grief.</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119976:17"/>
                  <l>And, therefore, now il'e tell you, in what ſtate</l>
                  <l>You find me, that you may rejoyce thereat,</l>
                  <l>By making you aſſur'd, that you have wrought</l>
                  <l>A <hi>work,</hi> which in it ſelf rewards hath brought</l>
                  <l>That will requite it fully, though I liv'd,</l>
                  <l>To let ſlip out of mind, what I receiv'd.</l>
                  <l>Then, told him all, that is before expreſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſo much more as did infer the reſt</l>
                  <l>That might have follow'd, if GOD had not ſent</l>
                  <l>His <hi>charity,</hi> my ruine to prevent.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The ſame <hi>impreſſion,</hi> which his <hi>Act</hi> had made</l>
                  <l>On <hi>me,</hi> my <hi>words</hi> on him, effected had;</l>
                  <l>And, I am confident, that, had <hi>I</hi> given</l>
                  <l>To him, the greateſt <hi>gift,</hi> on this ſide Heav'n,</l>
                  <l>He had not gone away, with more content</l>
                  <l>Then, in his being made an <hi>inſtrument,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a <hi>timely mercy;</hi> and, that he</l>
                  <l>So opportunely too, ſhould meet with me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now judg, if this be true, which I proteſt</l>
                  <l>(Except the words, wherein it is expreſt,</l>
                  <l>And, ſome few circumſtances, to ſupply</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſtory,</hi> with a <hi>formal decency,</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>real truth;</hi> and no <hi>poetick ſtrain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More adding, then the <hi>Eſſence</hi> did contain.</l>
                  <l>Judg now, what, I, could honeſtly have leſſe</l>
                  <l>Hereof declar'd, then here I do expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Conſid'ring what he was to me, till then;</l>
                  <l>And, what <hi>I</hi> was to many other men.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, at their <hi>dore,</hi> for whom <hi>I</hi> had of late,</l>
                  <l>My life adventur'd; loſt my whole Eſtate;</l>
                  <l>(And thoſe expos'd, who were more dear to me</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>life,</hi> and <hi>livelyhood,</hi> deſtroy'd to be)</l>
                  <l>Ev'n at their <hi>dore,</hi> I, periſhing was left</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>credit,</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> at once bereft:</l>
                  <l>To let me thereby know, and knowing, heed,</l>
                  <l>That in the <hi>times of triall,</hi> and of need,</l>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119976:17"/>
                  <l>Tis none of thoſe <hi>Acquaintance,</hi> or thoſe <hi>Friends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>we our ſelves</hi> get, or whoſe <hi>love</hi> attends</l>
                  <l>On our <hi>Proſperities;</hi> nor that, which we</l>
                  <l>Think, <hi>obligations,</hi> upon them to be;</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>publick Faith,</hi> nor <hi>Vows,</hi> nor <hi>Proteſtations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Either of <hi>Princes, Parliaments</hi> or <hi>Nations;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor that which is, nor that, which we ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>A <hi>merit</hi> in Us, (or, for <hi>Virtue</hi> goes)</l>
                  <l>Which, for <hi>helps,</hi> are to be relide upon,</l>
                  <l>In great extremities; But, <hi>GOD,</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>And, that, in our <hi>Deſertions,</hi> he, can make</l>
                  <l>Not only, <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> pity on us take;</l>
                  <l>But, alſo, from the malice of our <hi>Foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Raiſe us up <hi>help,</hi> ſalve <hi>mortall wounds,</hi> by <hi>blows;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cure us by <hi>ſickneſs;</hi> make us rich, by loſſes:</l>
                  <l>Give us true <hi>joy,</hi> in <hi>grief;</hi> Content, in <hi>Croſſes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>life,</hi> by <hi>dying;</hi> and the firſt beginning</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>juſtifying righteouſneſs,</hi> by <hi>ſinning:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, by the hiding (for a time) his <hi>Face,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſſurances</hi> of <hi>everlaſting grace:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to confirm my oft <hi>experiment</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hereof; GOD, made this <hi>Friend</hi> an <hi>Inſtrument,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To give me, of that <hi>mercy,</hi> one <hi>pledg</hi> more,</l>
                  <l>Of which, he gave me many, heretofore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And yet, this is not all; for, ere thoſe <hi>weights</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which lay upon me; and the many <hi>ſtreights,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then preſſing me, removed were and paſt,</l>
                  <l>(Which, ſome yeers, and ſome months to boot, did laſt)</l>
                  <l>In times of like need, he continued on</l>
                  <l>That <hi>work of mercy,</hi> thus by him began;</l>
                  <l>Till, in this manner, he, upon his ſcore,</l>
                  <l>Had ſet me, <hi>twenty hundred Crowns,</hi> and more,</l>
                  <l>Without deſiring, <hi>Band,</hi> or <hi>Bill,</hi> or <hi>Note,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To teſtifie the lending of one groat;</l>
                  <l>Or urging me, betwixt <hi>our ſelves,</hi> to ſay</l>
                  <l>I ow'd him ought, or that I would <hi>repay.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119976:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119976:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119976:19"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus much for this time: For, tis cold, and late;</l>
                  <l>And, that you may have time to ruminate</l>
                  <l>On what is ſaid; ile now break off, and borrow</l>
                  <l>An hour or two, from my <hi>affairs</hi> to morrow,</l>
                  <l>So much, of what remaineth, to recite</l>
                  <l>As ſeemeth pertinent: And ſo, <hi>good night.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="canto">
               <head>The third <hi>CANTO.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Author, <hi>ſheweth to what</hi> end,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>This</hi> Poem, <hi>was</hi> deſign'd, <hi>and</hi> pen'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Next, he proceeedeth to unfold</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What, is begun, and left untold</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Relating to his</hi> Friend, <hi>and Him;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, gives you then, a breathing time.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHen I have ſpent the <hi>day,</hi> as oft I do,</l>
                  <l>In vvheeling round, and trudging to and fro,</l>
                  <l>Through that <hi>meander,</hi> which do what I can</l>
                  <l>Still further leads, (then when I firſt began)</l>
                  <l>From my deſired reſt; and, nothing leaves me,</l>
                  <l>But new aſſurance, that the <hi>World</hi> deceives me;</l>
                  <l>And yet ſtill keeps me active, with a thought</l>
                  <l>That, I am thereby doing what I ought;</l>
                  <l>(Becauſe, ev'n by perſuing what is vain,</l>
                  <l>A knowledg of ſome uſefulnes I gain,</l>
                  <l>Which els could not be had) <hi>I</hi> take content</l>
                  <l>In ſuffering what I labour to prevent;</l>
                  <l>Permitting <hi>GOD,</hi> to order as he pleaſes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Me,</hi> and my <hi>ſomething,</hi> and my <hi>nothing neſſes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, in the <hi>night,</hi> when all to reſt are gone;</l>
                  <l>I muſe on things more worthy thinking on,</l>
                  <l>And, how, to others, and my ſelf, I may</l>
                  <l>Add ſomewhat, by our loſſes in the day.</l>
                  <l>Nor are my watchings, in that ſtollen leiſure,</l>
                  <l>So painfull, as ſome think; but full of pleaſure.</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:119976:19"/>
                  <l>Nor do my ſolitary <hi>Muſings</hi> tend</l>
                  <l>To that deceitfull, and unfruitfull <hi>end,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As is perhaps thought, in thoſe lucubrations,</l>
                  <l>Wherein I take my loanly recreations;</l>
                  <l>For, that, which me all night doth waking keep,</l>
                  <l>Refreſheth more my <hi>ſpirit,</hi> then my <hi>ſleep.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>ſubject,</hi> which this hour employes my pen,</l>
                  <l>Makes my <hi>dead friend,</hi> to live with me agen:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I,</hi> viſit him, and oft he viſits me</l>
                  <l>With inter-courſes, which no eyes can ſee.</l>
                  <l>Within my <hi>Chamber;</hi> (none els being there)</l>
                  <l>Me thinks, we two, as if alone we were</l>
                  <l>Converſe together, and he brings unto</l>
                  <l>My memory, and thought, what <hi>I</hi> ſhould do</l>
                  <l>To order ſo my <hi>life,</hi> that when <hi>I</hi> dye,</l>
                  <l>No <hi>living ſoul</hi> may be more glad as <hi>I.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sometime, with him <hi>I</hi> walk unto his grave,</l>
                  <l>To view what kind of lodgings <hi>dead men</hi> have,</l>
                  <l>And whether <hi>I</hi> can, ſee among them, there,</l>
                  <l>Such dreadfull things, as <hi>fleſh and blood</hi> doth fear.</l>
                  <l>Yea, there, at midnight <hi>I</hi> have with him been,</l>
                  <l>And every corner of the grave have ſeen,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Contemplation,</hi> (which ſees many ſights,</l>
                  <l>Not to be view'd by ordinary lights)</l>
                  <l>Yet there <hi>I</hi> did behold no greater dread,</l>
                  <l>Then when <hi>I</hi> ſleep moſt ſweetly in my bed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sometimes, he comes into my <hi>mind,</hi> and brings</l>
                  <l>A multitude of <hi>temporary things</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be by many thought of, who yet live,</l>
                  <l>And were of that late <hi>Repreſentative,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which from it honor, and, it being, fell,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe they nor <hi>beleev'd,</hi> nor <hi>acted</hi> vvell.</l>
                  <l>Of ſomethings too, that neerly vvill concern</l>
                  <l>The <hi>wiſe,</hi> (till they are grovvn too <hi>wiſe</hi> to learn)</l>
                  <l>He me remembers, by thoſe <hi>conferences</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which vve oft had, vvhen he enjoy'd his <hi>ſenſes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:119976:20"/>
                  <l>And, whereupon, <hi>I</hi> oft did more then gueſſe</l>
                  <l>At what was verifide in their <hi>ſucceſſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, and ſometimes, he makes me think upon</l>
                  <l>The <hi>preſent Powre,</hi> and on what's yet undone,</l>
                  <l>And ſhould be done, and will be done, ere long,</l>
                  <l>Unles, it grows, in ſelf opinion ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>And ſleights that counſel, which may ſave the State,</l>
                  <l>As their <hi>Foregoers</hi> did, till 'twas too late</l>
                  <l>Sometime, the thought of him, tranſlates me hence</l>
                  <l>To Heav'n; where, what tranſcends intelligence</l>
                  <l>And my expreſſion, is to me diſclos'd,</l>
                  <l>By fraction, and by notions diſcompos'd;</l>
                  <l>Which, nay the leſſe a certainty declare</l>
                  <l>Of ſome things, which for edifying are.</l>
                  <l>Sometime again (for we can any whither</l>
                  <l>Go ſafely) we deſcend to <hi>Hell</hi> together</l>
                  <l>By <hi>contemplation;</hi> and there, take full views</l>
                  <l>Of that which on Hypocriſie enſues;</l>
                  <l>And, on each other failing, and offence,</l>
                  <l>Perpetuating an <hi>Impenitence;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, thence, aſſume occaſion to improve</l>
                  <l>My thank fulnes, for that eternall love</l>
                  <l>By whom I am ſecured from that place,</l>
                  <l>Through his <hi>preventing,</hi> and <hi>aſſiſting grace.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>By thinking upon him, who in his grave</l>
                  <l>Lies thoughtles, of what thinkings I can have</l>
                  <l>Thus, I my ſelf employ; and, by <hi>things paſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The ordering of <hi>future things</hi> forecaſt;</l>
                  <l>And, find a means whereby I do refreſh</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Spirit,</hi> whilſt impriſon'd in the <hi>Fleſh</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And wherefore, judg you, I my time thus ſpend?</l>
                  <l>Is it to tell the <hi>World I</hi> had a <hi>Friend?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How vain were that! ſince, <hi>I</hi> am not to know</l>
                  <l>It cares not, whether <hi>I</hi> have <hi>Friends,</hi> or no.</l>
                  <l>And, loves to hear of no reſpect that's ſhown</l>
                  <l>To any, whom ſhe takes not for her own.</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:119976:20"/>
                  <l>Is it to gain a gratiouſnes with thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who, have, what he hath left at their diſpoſe?</l>
                  <l>That were to fall, ten thouſand leagues below</l>
                  <l>My <hi>ſpirit;</hi> and more baſe in <hi>me,</hi> would ſhow</l>
                  <l>Then it would do in them, to look upon</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a thought, what, here, by me is done,</l>
                  <l>For, theſe my <hi>retributions,</hi> are as free</l>
                  <l>From <hi>ſelf ends,</hi> as his <hi>bounty</hi> was to me,</l>
                  <l>And, rather ſhould be paid back, ten time double,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>I</hi> would looſe my freedom for that buble.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is to pleaſe, his near and dear <hi>relations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With large <hi>applauſes,</hi> and <hi>commemorations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of him that's gone? Alas! that doth but keep</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sorrows</hi> awake, which els would fall aſleep.</l>
                  <l>Doth but his knowledg in the <hi>fieſh</hi> renew,</l>
                  <l>Which keeps his better being, from their view;</l>
                  <l>Adds brine to thirſt; and to devouring fire</l>
                  <l>Caſts Oyl, which makes it but to flame the higher:</l>
                  <l>And, if no better uſe, could hence be rais'd,</l>
                  <l>It came to far leſſe, then, not to be prais'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is it to <hi>honor him,</hi> that's in his <hi>Grave?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That were the ſimpleſt thought the <hi>fool</hi> could have,</l>
                  <l>What <hi>honor</hi> can they want, who tryumph there,</l>
                  <l>Where ſulnes of eternall <hi>glories</hi> are?</l>
                  <l>What honor can he have from earthly things,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>glory,</hi> from a <hi>fame</hi> with paper vvings,</l>
                  <l>Which cannot make a flight for many miles,</l>
                  <l>Beyond the compaſſe of theſe <hi>Britiſh Iſles?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, from an <hi>Epitaph,</hi> on ſtone, or braſſe</l>
                  <l>Read by a fevv, in ſome obſcured place?</l>
                  <l>Or, hovv vvill it concern, or pleaſe him novv,</l>
                  <l>Who, to himſelf, vvould not, in life, allovv</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>attributes</hi> of <hi>honor,</hi> vvhich appear'd</l>
                  <l>Then due; nor, for an empty <hi>title</hi> car'd?</l>
                  <l>And, vvould have been diſpleas'd, if he had knowvvn</l>
                  <l>I, vvould on him, this <hi>trifle,</hi> have beſtovvn,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:119976:21"/>
                  <l>(Onely becauſe, it to his honor tends)</l>
                  <l>Although, therewith, compos'd to other ends?</l>
                  <l>Beſide, (although it ſomwhat may concern</l>
                  <l>His <hi>reputation</hi>) I am not to learn</l>
                  <l>That theſe <hi>Blaſts,</hi> for the moſt part, oftner rear</l>
                  <l>A duſt, to cloud it, then preſerve it clear;</l>
                  <l>Or, ſtirs up, <hi>envy, hate,</hi> or <hi>evill-will,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To brawl, which elſe (it may be) had lain ſtill.</l>
                  <l>For, to the Flower that ſpreads the faireſt blooms,</l>
                  <l>The Cankerworm and Caterpiller comes.</l>
                  <l>Moreover, they, <hi>who leaſt deſerving</hi> are</l>
                  <l>May in this kind of honor have a ſhare</l>
                  <l>With beſt Deſert; and buy, with what was theirs,</l>
                  <l>A better <hi>Monument</hi> then this appears.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is it for ſome advantages deſign'd</l>
                  <l>Unto my ſelf? ſure no; for none I find</l>
                  <l>Hereby acquirable; nor had I brought</l>
                  <l>My poverty to light, if I had ſought</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Self-honor;</hi> ſeeing, there is nothing more</l>
                  <l>Diſhonourable thought, then to be <hi>poore.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Well then; if it were neither ſo nor ſo,</l>
                  <l>What is my purpoſe, in what now I do?</l>
                  <l>Ev'n this, That, from the <hi>beſt man</hi> whom I knew</l>
                  <l>Here living, <hi>I</hi> might ſet forth to your view</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſelf-deniall,</hi> through the want of which</l>
                  <l>The Common-wealth grows poore, and poore men rich.</l>
                  <l>That, alſo, by him, in whoſe <hi>charity,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>GOD,</hi> did appear, in my neceſſity,</l>
                  <l>Others may be provok'd, through his examples,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew more love unto thoſe <hi>living Temples,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In which he dwelleth; and, at leaſt, forbear</l>
                  <l>To ruine them, although they have no care</l>
                  <l>Of their Repair: For, this is one of thoſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deficiencies,</hi> which multiplies our woes,</l>
                  <l>And, through defect, whereof our <hi>former coſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>preſent hopes,</hi> will ſuddenly be loſt,</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119976:21"/>
                  <l>As they have been; unleſs we do with ſpeed</l>
                  <l>Put, what is yet but <hi>words,</hi> into a Deed;</l>
                  <l>Not dreaming ſtill, that, we from GOD can hide,</l>
                  <l>What is by <hi>men,</hi> apparently eſpide:</l>
                  <l>For, though we will not ſee, what we behold,</l>
                  <l>Nor credit what we know true, being told,</l>
                  <l>It ſhall, in ſpight of all our impudence,</l>
                  <l>Let in a <hi>Fear,</hi> againſt which, no defence</l>
                  <l>Can poſſibly be made; and, then, the <hi>doom</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We fear'd in ſecret, openly ſhall come.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, of this <hi>ſelf-deniall</hi> vvas a <hi>Teacher,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, and as vvell a <hi>Pattern</hi> as a <hi>Preacher</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who, taught vvith <hi>power,</hi> ſuch principles as theſe,</l>
                  <l>And, not as do our <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I vvrote this partly likewiſe, in requital</l>
                  <l>Of his rare <hi>kindneſs;</hi> and by his recitall</l>
                  <l>Of vvhat he vvas, to ſtir up imitation</l>
                  <l>In all thoſe vvho had any near relation</l>
                  <l>Unto his <hi>fleſhly being;</hi> and thereby,</l>
                  <l>To pay my debt to his <hi>poſterity;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, that (if vvell improved) it might be</l>
                  <l>Some <hi>retribution,</hi> for his love to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, (in the <hi>firſt place,</hi> though <hi>I</hi> name it <hi>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt</hi>)</l>
                  <l>This <hi>opportunity I</hi> have embrac'd,</l>
                  <l>To keep ſtill viſible, before mine eyes,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Object,</hi> vvhich the vvorld doth moſt deſpiſe</l>
                  <l>To look upon; ev'n that, diſgracefull, poore,</l>
                  <l>And lovve eſtate, in vvhich <hi>I,</hi> heretofore</l>
                  <l>Was friendleſs left; and, in hovv juſt a time,</l>
                  <l>GOD, ſent me full Deliverance, by <hi>him;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One,</hi> from a <hi>Thouſand</hi> choſe, to ſignifie</l>
                  <l>Thus much; that, (notvvithſtanding they vvhom, <hi>I,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Remembred often; me remembred not)</l>
                  <l>His <hi>everlaſting love,</hi> vvas not forgot.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Having novv ſhevvn the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of my <hi>Rime,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> vvill return again to ſpeak of him</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:119976:22"/>
                  <l>Who cauſed this <hi>diſcourſe,</hi> which I am in;</l>
                  <l>And, where I left <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ff, there, I will begin.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Before, the bounty, which from him did come,</l>
                  <l>Amounted to the fore expreſſed ſum,</l>
                  <l>Aſhamed in my ſelf, to ſee how far</l>
                  <l>He had ingag'd me, without taking care</l>
                  <l>Of reimburſement; unto him I ſent</l>
                  <l>Unask, a true and full acknowledgment</l>
                  <l>Of all I had received: But, to my hand,</l>
                  <l>He back returned it, with this command</l>
                  <l>That, to no Perſon, <hi>I</hi> a word ſhould ſay</l>
                  <l>Of what had paſt betwixt us, in that way.</l>
                  <l>For, well <hi>I</hi> know, ſaid he, both <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall get but diſadvantages thereby.</l>
                  <l>The World, is full of envy, and malicious,</l>
                  <l>Making to us, our beſt works moſt pernitious.</l>
                  <l>They who in her affairs, are chiefly wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And, view, our actions, with meer carnal eyes,</l>
                  <l>Will judg me but a fool; and, think perchance,</l>
                  <l>Your <hi>wit,</hi> hath wrought out of my ignorance</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>eaſines,</hi> that, which is an effect</l>
                  <l>Of GODS good <hi>providence,</hi> and my <hi>reſpect:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Keep it in ſecret therefore; for, from thence,</l>
                  <l>There can ariſe no miſchief, or offence.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe Reaſons charm'd me; and, with much ado,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſilence kept, becauſe, he wil'd it ſo.</l>
                  <l>Only, (ſome few dayes after he forbid</l>
                  <l>This to be mention'd) him, <hi>I</hi> friendly chid</l>
                  <l>By theſe enſuing <hi>Verſes,</hi> which are next</l>
                  <l>Inſerted here, as not beſide my <hi>Text.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SIR, though, ſo friendly, you to me have been,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, to forget it, were a</hi> mortall ſin,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet, I am</hi> one, <hi>whom divers do ſuppoſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To make no difference, betwixt</hi> Friends, <hi>and</hi> Foes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In my</hi> reproovings; <hi>And, if that be true,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My</hi> worthy noble Friend, <hi>then, have at</hi> You.</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:119976:22"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For, you forget your ſelf, and ſtrive to clime</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To heights, ſo unfrequented at this time,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, I ſuppoſe, I am in conſcience tide</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your</hi> temper, <hi>and your</hi> practiſes, <hi>to chide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leſt by ſoft-hearted kindnes, and compaſſion</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(With ſuch like</hi> vertues, <hi>now grown out of faſhion)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>It may deſervedly be ſaid, by ſome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>One of theſe</hi> Sectarie <hi>you are become,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>And, of theſe</hi> Hereticks <hi>thought worſe then</hi> Turks)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who ſhew their true</hi> beleeving, <hi>by their</hi> works;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, ſeem to bring their ſimple cuſtome hither,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of living well, and lovingly together.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fy! have you honor'd been to ſit among</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The wiſeſt of this</hi> Common-wealth <hi>ſo long?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And where, the men, who do themſelves ſuppeſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To be (at leaſt) the wiſeſt part of theſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Can many dayes, weeks, moneths, yea many years,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hear</hi> Widdows <hi>out-cries, and ſee Orphans tears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Without the caſting of one look aſide</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On thoſe, who by their path, ſtand Crucifide?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And will you ſo degenerate from them</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe</hi> practiſes, <hi>are</hi> patterns <hi>for the</hi> time</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To look on him, whom they have trampled on,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And leſt, as to the world-ward, quite undone?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Can you deſcend ſo low, to fix your eyes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>On thoſe, whom</hi> men in honor <hi>do deſpiſe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yea, in a manner, ſeek unto them, too,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who are diſtreſt, (before they ſeek to you?)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e them to be releev'd, by your expen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(As if you ſuffer'd, by their indigence)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And charge them, that they tell it unto none,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As if a</hi> deed of darknes, <hi>you had done?</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beleeve, it SIR, this is a</hi> novelty,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which doth betray you, ſo apparently</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, were it known, your</hi> beſt Friends <hi>would not ſtick,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To voice you, publickly, a</hi> Schiſmatick.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119976:23"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scarce parallel'd: For, you in this divide</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From all I know, in all the World beſide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Excepting one or two; and</hi> you, <hi>and</hi> they</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Make up that little</hi> Congregation <hi>may,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With whom CHRIST promis'd he would preſent be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though it conſiſted but of</hi> tvvo, <hi>or</hi> three:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And which was promiſed, (for ought I hear)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Though none of them, a</hi> Prieſt, <hi>or</hi> Prelate <hi>were.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The circumſtances heeded in your</hi> acts,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Do very ſtrangely aggravate the</hi> facts.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Had it been only, in a</hi> humor <hi>done,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or, in a</hi> fit, <hi>but</hi> once, <hi>or</hi> tvvice <hi>alone</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(As works of</hi> charity, <hi>are, now and then,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Performed, and repented of agen,)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or, had that charity, from you diſtil'd,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But, drop by drop; or had it forth been fil'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By thimbles full, (as unto thoſe we give,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Our</hi> Aquavitae, <hi>whom we faint perceive)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Had it been ſo, or ſo, I ſhould have thought</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So much thereof, as I in reaſon ought;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(Though, with much more reſpect then yet I ſee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My publike ſervices, will thought on be)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And would have ſtriv'd, as far as I was able</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To make the</hi> gifts, <hi>and</hi> thanks, <hi>proportionable,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As wiſe men do; or, ſome way complemented,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And cuſtomary ſervices preſented,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>According to the faſhion: But, the</hi> courſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That you have took, Acknowledgments inforce</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beyond all</hi> Preſidents: <hi>For, Sir, you ſtretch</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your noblenes ſo far beyond the reach</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of my weak</hi> faculties, <hi>to retribute</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Acknowledgments, <hi>which therunto may ſuit;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yea, and ſo</hi> oft, <hi>ſo</hi> long, <hi>ſo</hi> gen'rouſly</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You have releeved my neceſſity;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, therewith overcharged, I am fain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To break out of the ro de, into a ſtrain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119976:23"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Some way extravagantly to declare,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As often in ſuch</hi> ſtraights <hi>as theſe we are</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Conſtrain'd to do; And, as once</hi> Peter <hi>did</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When through CHRISTS</hi> manhood, <hi>he the</hi> Godhead <hi>ſpid;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, when, he having fiſh'd all night for nought,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And drew a</hi> whole ſhip lading <hi>at one draught,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>He cride out, LORD,</hi> go from me <hi>(get thee gone)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For I confeſſe my ſelf a ſinfull one.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As, is the</hi> Fruit, <hi>ſo, may the</hi> ſeaſon <hi>be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A token of the nature of the</hi> Tree:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>(As that which cometh by the Rivers ſide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, whereby</hi> Righteous men <hi>are typifide</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Illuſtrates well,) I, therefore, in reſpect</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ev'n of the time, may ſomewhat here object,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſhow, yet farther, how you rend from thoſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who have our</hi> earthly things, <hi>at their diſpoſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For, at ſuch times of need, ſtill, ayd you lent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As if by GOD himſelf, it had been ſent,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who, only, knew my wants; and unto whom</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I, only ſhew them, when ſuch great ones come:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Becauſe, in greateſt wants, I do perceive</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Men readier to</hi> deſtroy, <hi>then to</hi> relieve.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such, is the ſtate of many in diſtreſſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such, is the hate, of thoſe, who do oppreſſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The rightly timing of a</hi> benefit,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Doth, very often, more then double it:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, though ſuch</hi> charity, <hi>may, in theſe dayes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Return you little preſent</hi> gain, <hi>or</hi> praiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet, GOD obſerves it; and, as ſure, as he</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Will of a</hi> cup of Water <hi>heed full be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beſtow'd on him who doth aſſume the name,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of his</hi> Diſciple, <hi>(although not the ſame)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You</hi> timely, <hi>and your</hi> large benevolence,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Shall have a timely, and large recompence.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Me, in due ſeaſon, GOD not only ſhall</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Enable too, ſome way, to pay you all;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119976:24"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But, add mean time, a bleſſing to defray</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That intereſt which he doth yet delay:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, in that place, where ſome of thoſe (I fear)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who, me oppreſt, will tremble to appear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You, ſhall be welcomed, with</hi> come ye bleſſed,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who fed, and cloath'd me, when I was diſtreſſed.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſe things conſider'd,</hi> this, <hi>which I begun,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pretending ſome</hi> reproof, <hi>intendeth none:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But, rather, is, (that debts be not forgot)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> memorandum <hi>only, or a</hi> note,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Subſcribed with my hand, for intimation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That,</hi> you, <hi>with</hi> me, <hi>ſhall have his</hi> obligation</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe word is paſs'd already to reſtore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whatever ſhall be lent unto the poor:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, who, doth good to every one intend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whoſe heart he moves, the</hi> needy <hi>to befriend.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet, that, mean time, I may not failing be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To pay as much in hand, as lies in me;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Receive this</hi> Benediction. <hi>Whenſoere</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The day of</hi> fiery tryall <hi>ſhall appear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To prove your</hi> Faith, <hi>and purge you quite from all</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your</hi> ſelfnes: <hi>which ere long time will befall:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let, then, your</hi> Faith <hi>be ſtrong, and GOD be ſeen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> friend <hi>to</hi> you, <hi>as</hi> you <hi>to</hi> me <hi>have been:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And let your charity before him ſtand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To manacle, and weaken every hand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That would oppreſs thoſe, whom you leave behind:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let them GODS favour, in all troubles find:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be ſafe preſerved, in all</hi> times, and <hi>places,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By his</hi> free mercies, <hi>and</hi> preventing Graces;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And let this</hi> prayer, <hi>ſtil, about GOD'S Throne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Be fluttering, till he ſaith,</hi> ſo be it done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Verſes,</hi> for his large <hi>benevolence</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were, for a long time, all his evidence.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:119976:24"/>
                  <l>Nor would he more receive, though many a time</l>
                  <l>Security was offer'd unto him.</l>
                  <l>And, once, it was in words like theſe, denide:</l>
                  <l>When firſt I your neceſſity ſupplide,</l>
                  <l>My <hi>purpoſe</hi> was not, meerly to relieve</l>
                  <l>Your preſent need; but, likewiſe, ayd to give</l>
                  <l>That, by your own <hi>endeavour,</hi> (with my coſt)</l>
                  <l>You might recover that which you have loſt.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>State,</hi> hath no part ſatisfied, yet,</l>
                  <l>Of your allow'd, and overlong due <hi>debt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, till that ſhall be done, I will expect</l>
                  <l>No <hi>payment,</hi> neither ought to that <hi>effect.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But, his <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> having made me ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>That, to recover, which had been by wrong</l>
                  <l>Detained from me, in a private hand;</l>
                  <l>(And having ſomwhat more at my command)</l>
                  <l>I thought my ſelf oblig'd (as I was able)</l>
                  <l>To render ſome returns proportionable</l>
                  <l>To my Eſtate. So, he accepts, at laſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Security</hi> for part, and left the reſt;</l>
                  <l>(Of which, to him, I ſomewhat yearly brought)</l>
                  <l>Without his asking, as expecting ought</l>
                  <l>(By any thing expreſſed) untill that,</l>
                  <l>Were pay'd me, which is owing by the <hi>State;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, till the reſidue, I could repay,</l>
                  <l>By ſome enablement another way.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, ſhews it is no frivilous occaſion</l>
                  <l>From whence this <hi>Poem</hi> ſprings; or, <hi>Obligation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be as inconſiderable, ſlighted</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>me</hi> to this acknowledgment invited:</l>
                  <l>But rather, in regard of GOD, and <hi>Man,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An act, which ought, as fully as <hi>I</hi> can</l>
                  <l>To be expreſt; That, for it I might give</l>
                  <l>The <hi>praiſe</hi> to GOD, and, men th' <hi>example</hi> have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, by his <hi>charity,</hi> GOD'S love appears:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I was,</hi> thereby, preſerved many years</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:119976:25"/>
                  <l>From periſhing: Thereby, likewiſe, together</l>
                  <l>VVith that aſſiſtance, which I had from other</l>
                  <l>Concurring helps, (which have the ſame way, been</l>
                  <l>To me by <hi>GOD'S</hi> good providence, ſent in.)</l>
                  <l>I got to be poſſeſſor of the <hi>gate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of thoſe, who were mine enemies of late;</l>
                  <l>And, thereby, alſo, partly to expreſſe</l>
                  <l>To others, in their need, my <hi>thankfulneſs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thereto, the Noble, and much Honored</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> and <hi>Dixwell,</hi> ayde contributed,</l>
                  <l>Among ſome others, who are not forgot.</l>
                  <l>Although their kindnes I here mention not;</l>
                  <l>Yea, GOD, for me, ſo likewiſe, did diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>The <hi>purpoſe,</hi> of my avaritious <hi>foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, doubly, it advantag'd me, and more</l>
                  <l>Then all thoſe <hi>loving friends</hi> had done before.</l>
                  <l>VVhich, ſuddenly improoving my Eſtate</l>
                  <l>Beyond, what I did hope, or aimed at;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>World</hi> doth ſeem to think, and ſome do ſay,</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I,</hi> to thrive, have practiſed her way;</l>
                  <l>And, on my conſcience, would now love me too,</l>
                  <l>If, truly, ſhe beleev'd it had been ſo:</l>
                  <l>For, nothing renders her, a <hi>Foe</hi> to me</l>
                  <l>But, that ſhe fears my <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>deeds</hi> agree.</l>
                  <l>And, that, though baits, and ſnares for me are laid</l>
                  <l>To ſerve her ends, I ſhall not be betraid.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now, having finiſhed this little <hi>ſtory,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich hath a neer relation to GOD'S glory</l>
                  <l>As well as to the honour of my <hi>Friend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With ſome brief <hi>inferences, I</hi> will end.</l>
                  <l>But, leſt, theſe may detain you overlong,</l>
                  <l>Here pauſe; and read them, in the following <hi>Song.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="canto">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119976:25"/>
               <head>The fourth <hi>CANTO.</hi>
               </head>
               <argument>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> Chriſtian love, <hi>the large extents;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ſad, the bad, the mad events</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of</hi> diſcord, <hi>here the</hi> Muſe <hi>diſplaies;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That Idol SELFNES open laies.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Some other things to heed commends,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And, then, with</hi> praiſe, <hi>and</hi> Prayer <hi>ends.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
               </argument>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat ſhall that <hi>Muſing</hi> profir, which affords</l>
                  <l>Nothing but bare <hi>Relations,</hi> or meer <hi>words?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, what will things avail, that ſhall be read,</l>
                  <l>Concerning thoſe, who ſleep among the <hi>dead</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If no advantages at all they give</l>
                  <l>To benefit, or better thoſe that <hi>live?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Sure none; Leſt, therefore, theſe may juſtly paſſe</l>
                  <l>For tingling <hi>Cymbals,</hi> or for ſounding <hi>Braſſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some uſeful <hi>notes,</hi> or <hi>notions,</hi> ile diſcover</l>
                  <l>On this <hi>occaſion,</hi> ere <hi>I</hi> paſſe it over.</l>
                  <l>And though I cannot <hi>talk,</hi> as others do,</l>
                  <l>He <hi>preach</hi> my way; and, preach to purpoſe too.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of many things, which merit mention may,</l>
                  <l>Wherein my <hi>Friend,</hi> hath pattern'd out the <hi>way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>walking,</hi> and of <hi>practiſe;</hi> three things, here,</l>
                  <l>Shall be inſiſted on, as thoſe that are</l>
                  <l>Deſerving ſpeciall heed: Such, as (if we</l>
                  <l>Well imitate) a true <hi>ALL HEAL</hi> ſhall be:</l>
                  <l>End all <hi>Quarrels;</hi> Take off, from our eyes</l>
                  <l>The blinding <hi>ſcales,</hi> and <hi>filmes</hi> of <hi>prejudice</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which keeps us dark, and from a right perceiving,</l>
                  <l>of <hi>truth,</hi> and, in a wilfull <hi>misheleeving.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An <hi>imitation</hi> thereof, would bring hither</l>
                  <l>Outward, and inward <hi>peace;</hi> and knit together</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119976:26"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>CHRISTS</hi> diſunited <hi>members</hi> ſo, that <hi>love</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Would ripen knowledg; <hi>Knowledg</hi> help improve</l>
                  <l>A <hi>ſaving Faith;</hi> That <hi>Faith</hi> renevv the <hi>Will;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>will renewed,</hi> would GODS minde fulfill,</l>
                  <l>And therewith, ſo acquainted make us grow</l>
                  <l>That, we ſhould learn to <hi>Act,</hi> as vvell as <hi>know.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The firſt of theſe is <hi>Love; love,</hi> not extending</l>
                  <l>It ſelf, to <hi>theſe,</hi> or <hi>thoſe,</hi> but comprehending</l>
                  <l>All things <hi>created,</hi> with an <hi>imitation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of <hi>CHRIST,</hi> by meekneſs in his <hi>converſation</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With <hi>Publicans</hi> and ſinners; and, vvith ſuch</l>
                  <l>As <hi>knew</hi> but little, and <hi>beleev'd</hi> not much.</l>
                  <l>Such, vvas <hi>CHRISTS love;</hi> and (if <hi>I</hi> do not miſs)</l>
                  <l>According to <hi>man's meaſure,</hi> ſuch vvas his.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, though, that <hi>vail of fleſh</hi> vvhich others vvear,</l>
                  <l>And, that, vvhich clothed him, vvhen he vvas here,</l>
                  <l>Diſguiz'd his <hi>inward man,</hi> and made him paſs</l>
                  <l>For one of thoſe, vvho running of a <hi>Race</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth beat the air in vain; yet, they, vvhoſe eyes</l>
                  <l>Obſerved him vvhen he vvas neer the <hi>prize,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Savv, he had uſde the <hi>means,</hi> and choſe the <hi>ground,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which beſt advantag'd him, and would be crown'd,</l>
                  <l>When, many, at a loſs themſelves would find.</l>
                  <l>Who, better <hi>dieted,</hi> and <hi>diſciplin'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were thought to be; For, none could know ſo well</l>
                  <l>What beſt befitted him, as he might tell.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Near to his latter end, he had attain'd</l>
                  <l>Such love to all, and, therewith, ſo unfain'd</l>
                  <l>A longing both to win, and to be won</l>
                  <l>Unto the <hi>Truth,</hi> that, he was <hi>Fo</hi> to none</l>
                  <l>So much, as to himſelf: and, by <hi>forbearing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By <hi>hopefulneſs, long-ſuffering, patient hearing,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>meekneſs,</hi> without <hi>bitterneſs of ſpirit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>True <hi>quietneſs of heart</hi> he did inherit</l>
                  <l>Within himſelf; and waited, when GOD'S leiſure</l>
                  <l>Would of his <hi>grace,</hi> to others, fill the meaſure.</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119976:26"/>
                  <l>My cognizance of him, perſwades me ſo,</l>
                  <l>And, whether he thus perfect were, or no,</l>
                  <l>It ſerves the turn, as well to let us ſee</l>
                  <l>What <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> and every man ſhould be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, of this Chriſtian temper <hi>I</hi> had proof,</l>
                  <l>To make it forth, with evidence enough.</l>
                  <l>For, though in <hi>fundamentals</hi> we agreed,</l>
                  <l>Eſſentially (as by what did ſucced,</l>
                  <l>Is manifeſt) yea, though we did accord</l>
                  <l>In one GOD, in one <hi>CHRIST,</hi> one <hi>Faith,</hi> one <hi>word.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>One <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>hope;</hi> (as all true <hi>Chriſtians</hi> do,)</l>
                  <l>Yet, in ſome accidentall means thereto</l>
                  <l>We diſagree'd; yea, often, did diſſent</l>
                  <l>In ſome things, which 'twixt others made a <hi>rent.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, <hi>I</hi> was oft, ſo earneſt in diſpute,</l>
                  <l>His <hi>tenents</hi> to diſprove, and to confute,</l>
                  <l>That, they who ſhould have heard us, might have judg'd</l>
                  <l>Not <hi>me</hi> to <hi>him,</hi> but <hi>him</hi> to <hi>me,</hi> oblig'd,</l>
                  <l>And that like <hi>Paul</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d <hi>Barnabas,</hi> at leaſt,</l>
                  <l>A parting, would ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e followed our conteſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet, though we both ſtood firm, to what we thought</l>
                  <l>Nor loſſe of <hi>love,</hi> nor breach 'twixt us, it wrought;</l>
                  <l>But, rather, to each other kept us nearer,</l>
                  <l>The firmer in our friendſhip, and the dearer:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we both knew, that, one <hi>Judg</hi> we had,</l>
                  <l>In whom <hi>Atonement,</hi> would, at laſt, be made:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, we both intended, not that <hi>He,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, <hi>I,</hi> might conquer, but, Truth victor be:</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>I,</hi> might conquer, but, Truth victor be:</l>
                  <l>And, this declareth his <hi>deſerving,</hi> more</l>
                  <l>Then all, that <hi>I</hi> have ſaid of him before.</l>
                  <l>For, what man els, but he, would not have thought</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Obligations,</hi> ſhould my ſoul have brought</l>
                  <l>In bondage to his <hi>Judgment?</hi> or, at leaſt</l>
                  <l>Kept me from owning mine, by <hi>hot conteſt?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who els but he, would have continued on</l>
                  <l>His love, and bounty, unto ſuch a <hi>One</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119976:27"/>
                  <l>As thwarted his opinions? and, not rather</l>
                  <l>Have made me ſcatter what he holp to gather?</l>
                  <l>Converted former <hi>friendſhip,</hi> into hate,</l>
                  <l>And, ſought to ruine me, in my Eſtate?</l>
                  <l>Which had with eaſe been done; ſince, at that time,</l>
                  <l>My chief <hi>ſubſiſtance,</hi> was receiv'd from him.</l>
                  <l>But, of his <hi>judgment,</hi> what er'e think <hi>I</hi> might</l>
                  <l>I knew his <hi>love</hi> was firm; his heart upright;</l>
                  <l>And, this beleef of no man, <hi>I</hi> could have</l>
                  <l>Who gave his <hi>charity,</hi> to make a <hi>ſlave:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, who from bondage did my fleſh unbind</l>
                  <l>To lay a greater Thraldom, on my mind.</l>
                  <l>No, (though from <hi>ſervitude,</hi> he ſet me free)</l>
                  <l>If he, thus cruel, ſhould to others be.</l>
                  <l>Nay, though a <hi>King,</hi> with me ſhould ſhare his <hi>Throne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And prize me, as his chief <hi>elected one,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were he a <hi>Tyrant</hi> over other men,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> could not give him <hi>love,</hi> for <hi>love</hi> agen:</l>
                  <l>Nay, further (be it ſpoke with reverence</l>
                  <l>To him I ſpeak of, and without offence)</l>
                  <l>Could <hi>I</hi> believe that GOD, in whom <hi>I</hi> truſt</l>
                  <l>Were (though he lov'd me) cruel and unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> would not ſeek with him in Heav'n to dwell,</l>
                  <l>But, rather, go, and live alone in Hell.</l>
                  <l>For, he, that's with eſſential GOD delighted,</l>
                  <l>And, thereunto by hearty <hi>love</hi> united;</l>
                  <l>Should therewith feel to him, ſuch vertue giv'n,</l>
                  <l>As would tranſlate the <hi>loweſt Hell</hi> to <hi>Heav'n.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> fear, <hi>I</hi> go too high in my <hi>expreſſions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ile therefore ſtoop again, from theſe <hi>digreſſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſpeak what's poſſible to be beleev'd</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe, by whom this cannot be receiv'd.</l>
                  <l>And ſhew them, in my common <hi>ſtrain,</hi> how far</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Chriſtian love,</hi> the greateſt number are,</l>
                  <l>Who moſt profeſſe it; that, affect they may</l>
                  <l>A far more excellent, and better way,</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119976:27"/>
                  <l>If <hi>carnall luſts,</hi> will give them time to read it,</l>
                  <l>And, their <hi>ſelf-love,</hi> admit of <hi>Grace</hi> to heed it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It is not <hi>love,</hi> but cruelty in thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who, would on others <hi>conſciences</hi> impoſe</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Yoaks,</hi> or break the bands of <hi>loving kindnes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Becauſe, their <hi>friends</hi> have <hi>weakneſſes,</hi> or <hi>blindnes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay, (which of <hi>cruelties</hi> appears the worſt)</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, they would not be, from that divorſt,</l>
                  <l>Which is their <hi>comforts</hi> chief preſervative;</l>
                  <l>And, without which, none happily can live</l>
                  <l>Here, or hereafter; And, when doing ſo,</l>
                  <l>To theſe <hi>impoſers,</hi> no true good can do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What is a <hi>friend</hi> for; or, what better are</l>
                  <l>Thoſe <hi>friends,</hi> then <hi>foes,</hi> who neither can forbear</l>
                  <l>Nor help to bear, that Friends infirmities</l>
                  <l>With meeknes, whom he hath been pleas'd to prize?</l>
                  <l>But, beat the <hi>lame,</hi> becauſe, they cannot <hi>run;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leave him that's <hi>blind,</hi> becauſe he ſees no <hi>Sun;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, ſeperate from them, for that, which they</l>
                  <l>Would willingly diſclaim, and caſt away</l>
                  <l>If they were able; or, els, did not fear</l>
                  <l>They, thereby, <hi>ſinners</hi> againſt <hi>Conſcience,</hi> were?</l>
                  <l>Whereas, they rather ſhould with theſe abide,</l>
                  <l>To lead the <hi>lame;</hi> to be the <hi>blind-mans</hi> guide:</l>
                  <l>And, with <hi>long-ſuffring,</hi> to inſtruct the other,</l>
                  <l>Till he becomes a true <hi>beleeving Brother.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh! how far off! how far! are ſuch as thoſe</l>
                  <l>From imitating him, who lov'd his Foes?</l>
                  <l>(And dide to ſave them?) who perſue with hate</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>friends,</hi> for thoſe concerments, which relate</l>
                  <l>Unto themſelves alone? How far are ſuch</l>
                  <l>From loving them, who have offended much?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This temper at this time, is very rare,</l>
                  <l>For gen'rally almoſt, we bite and tear,</l>
                  <l>So barbarouſly, each others <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>fleeces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And rend <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Robes into ſo many peeces,</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119976:28"/>
                  <l>That, we ſeem rather <hi>Woolves,</hi> and <hi>doggs,</hi> then <hi>ſheep,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Belonging to that <hi>Flock</hi> which he doth keep.</l>
                  <l>Nor are <hi>they,</hi> only, Woolves in ſheeps array,</l>
                  <l>Who, thus their Woolviſh nature do betray,</l>
                  <l>But, ev'n on ſome of <hi>us,</hi> who of his Fold</l>
                  <l>Are <hi>Members,</hi> this, diſtemper doth lay hold.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ev'n we forſooth, for whom our GOD hath done</l>
                  <l>So much of late; we, <hi>we,</hi> who look upon</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves at this time, as a People choſe</l>
                  <l>By ſpecial <hi>providence,</hi> to ſcourge his <hi>Foes;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, to be they, whom he firſt cals to bring</l>
                  <l>Unto his <hi>Throne,</hi> our <hi>Everlaſting King,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>Banners LOVE;</hi> Ev'n we, have here of late,</l>
                  <l>Inſtead thereof, advanc'd the <hi>Flagg</hi> of <hi>HATE</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To be our <hi>Standard;</hi> and, the ſame diſplay</l>
                  <l>With as much virulency as we may</l>
                  <l>Againſt each other: Yea, againſt thoſe, too,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeek <hi>GOD'S face,</hi> as truly as we do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some of us, ſo aloft, our ſelves do carry</l>
                  <l>With hope of great atchievements <hi>temporary,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, we forget from whence we firſt aſcended;</l>
                  <l>Slight them, for whoſe ſakes, we have been befriended;</l>
                  <l>None loving, but our ſelves; and looking on</l>
                  <l>All els, as if the <hi>Earth,</hi> for us alone,</l>
                  <l>Had been created; and all others, born</l>
                  <l>For objects of our hatred, or our ſcorn:</l>
                  <l>And, leave them unrewarded, by whoſe hands</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ground</hi> was won, on which our <hi>building</hi> ſtands.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Some of us, on a <hi>ſpirituall account,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſuch an <hi>overweningnes</hi> do mount,</l>
                  <l>As if, we only, were the men, to whom</l>
                  <l>Belongs that <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which is yet to come:</l>
                  <l>Or, as if <hi>Heav'n,</hi> for none els were ordain'd,</l>
                  <l>But, thoſe, who are among us entertain'd;</l>
                  <l>Bound up to our <hi>Rules;</hi> marked, with our <hi>Prints;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, qualifide with our <hi>diſtinguiſhments:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119976:28"/>
                  <l>And, ſo bewitch't are we, by our own <hi>Dreams,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With that, which we have Preach'd upon thoſe <hi>Theams,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, if we take not heed, 'twill bring about</l>
                  <l>That <hi>miſchief,</hi> which we purpoſe to keep out.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For, we through want of <hi>love,</hi> are ſo devided,</l>
                  <l>By having <hi>this way,</hi> or els <hi>that way,</hi> ſided</l>
                  <l>To raiſe what others build up, or, in ſtriving</l>
                  <l>To raiſe a <hi>Babell,</hi> of our own contriving;</l>
                  <l>That, ſome perchance, may ſee the <hi>Dragons tail,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Swing once more over us, ere we prevail.</l>
                  <l>Yea, want of <hi>love,</hi> on all ſides, ſo <hi>miſteaches,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here, ſucn <hi>Obſtructions</hi> makes, and there, ſuch <hi>breaches</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That, we are like to make our <hi>common Foe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An eaſie paſſage, where he could not go.</l>
                  <l>Yet, 'tis not poſſible to make us wake</l>
                  <l>From our vain <hi>Dreams,</hi> a ſafer courſe to take;</l>
                  <l>Unles, GOD, ſhall, our <hi>Adderlike deaf ear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pence by ſome ſtranger <hi>charms,</hi> then, yet, we hear:</l>
                  <l>For, they are thought to ſpeak words moſt in ſeaſon,</l>
                  <l>Who ſpeak moſt <hi>impudently,</hi> and leaſt <hi>reaſon:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In which beſottednes, if he walk on</l>
                  <l>Much longer, as too long time we have done,</l>
                  <l>(Acting, as if we thought, to ſhew, our folly</l>
                  <l>Would be an argument to prove <hi>us holy.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And drive ſtill furiouſly againſt each other,</l>
                  <l>As if all ſhortly would be mad together,)</l>
                  <l>They, will not much miſtake therein, who ſhall</l>
                  <l>This Iſle, Great <hi>BEDLAM,</hi> now Great <hi>BRITAN</hi> call.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The other <hi>vertue,</hi> of my now <hi>dead Friend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which to our <hi>imitation,</hi> Ile commend,</l>
                  <l>Is, to be zealous, in the pulling down</l>
                  <l>Of our great <hi>Idol.</hi> now, more famous grown,</l>
                  <l>Then was <hi>Diana;</hi> and, ador'd by us,</l>
                  <l>Much more then ſhe was once, at <hi>Epheſus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That weak, that baſe, that deſpicable <hi>ELFE,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cal'd <hi>SELFNES,</hi> which, man ſets up in himſelf;</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:119976:29"/>
                  <l>And, for whoſe ſervices, and <hi>adoration,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We from all things within the whole <hi>Creation,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make <hi>patterns</hi> to our ſelves: And, not of theſe</l>
                  <l>Alone, make we <hi>fantaſtick images.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, of things alſo, which had neither <hi>birth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>being,</hi> on, or underneath the earth;</l>
                  <l>Neither within the <hi>water, ayr,</hi> or <hi>fire,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or any where, in lower place, or higher.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, is that <hi>God,</hi> which now is worſhip'd more,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Baal,</hi> and all thoſe <hi>Idols</hi> heretofore,</l>
                  <l>Which did provoke to wrath. There, are our <hi>loves</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Moſt fixt. Thereto, our <hi>Temples, Altars, Groves</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are conſecrated; and, what els, beſide</l>
                  <l>Whereby, an <hi>Idol</hi> may be glorifide.</l>
                  <l>Thereto, thoſe <hi>Tithes,</hi> thoſe <hi>Duties,</hi> thoſe <hi>Oblations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thanksgivings, Prayers,</hi> ſolemn <hi>Obſervations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All <hi>forms,</hi> and <hi>ceremonies,</hi> (whether taught</l>
                  <l>By <hi>truth,</hi> or, <hi>ſuperſtitiouſly</hi> in brought;)</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Governments,</hi> our <hi>Parliaments,</hi> our Laws,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Armies,</hi> our unjuſt, and <hi>righteous Cauſe;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> all our <hi>wiſdom,</hi> all our <hi>wealth;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>honor, beauty,</hi> with our <hi>youth,</hi> and <hi>health;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>righteouſnes</hi> (if we in us, have any;</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>wickedneſſes,</hi> (whereof we have many;)</l>
                  <l>Ev'n <hi>Scriptures, Judgments, mercies, Sacraments,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With what els, <hi>GOD</hi> ordains, or <hi>man</hi> invents,</l>
                  <l>Are all, by ſome among us, now converted,</l>
                  <l>(Or, rather, to ſpeak properly, perverted)</l>
                  <l>Some way to ſerve, as to advance the praiſe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>SELFNES,</hi> that great <hi>Idol</hi> of our dayes.</l>
                  <l>And, ſome, who <hi>vote,</hi> and ſpeak againſt it more</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>many;</hi> more, then <hi>any, her</hi> adore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt, who pretend, to ſerve the <hi>Common-weal,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do moſt intend, from thence to rob and ſteal</l>
                  <l>Wherewith, to ſacrifice before the <hi>ſhrine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of that lou'd <hi>Idol;</hi> which doth glare, and ſhine,</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119976:29"/>
                  <l>With <hi>jewels, gold,</hi> and thoſe <hi>embelliſhments,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich ſhould have been the publike <hi>Ornaments.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They, from poor <hi>Orphans,</hi> and ſad <hi>Widdows,</hi> tear</l>
                  <l>Their Garments, for that pſeudo-god to wear:</l>
                  <l>Pluck from their hungry mouths, their bread and meat,</l>
                  <l>For that devouring <hi>God</hi> of theirs to eat:</l>
                  <l>And, then, for his <hi>drink-offrings,</hi> pour forth floods</l>
                  <l>Of faithfull ſervants, Friends, and Childrens bloods.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt, who pretend true <hi>Juſtice</hi> to maintain,</l>
                  <l>Do more contend, to wrong thoſe who complain,</l>
                  <l>Then hovv to right them; that, thereby they may</l>
                  <l>Make <hi>innocents,</hi> this curſed <hi>Idols pray:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, to their <hi>faithfull friends,</hi> are moſt ſevere;</l>
                  <l>Either, to make a ſhevv, as if they vvere</l>
                  <l>Impartiall, or, perhaps, thereby, to pay</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> good <hi>deſert,</hi> the clean contrary vvay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt, vvho pretend to <hi>charity,</hi> do give</l>
                  <l>Either, in hope they, thereby ſhall receive</l>
                  <l>Some benefit; or, els in hope to raiſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Monument, or Trophie of <hi>ſelf praiſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And fevv out of a tendernes of heart,</l>
                  <l>Give, to releeve, or to revvard <hi>deſert.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt, vvho pretend to <hi>friendſhip,</hi> do but buy</l>
                  <l>With complements, or ſome cheap courteſie,</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſelf</hi> advantages; and, to more charge,</l>
                  <l>When they are put, it is but to inlarge</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>ſelfnes;</hi> and, ſome way thereby, among</l>
                  <l>Such other ends, to make their party ſtrong:</l>
                  <l>For, when unſerviceable, theſe are grown,</l>
                  <l>They caſt them off, as Perſons never known.</l>
                  <l>Yea, when the times doth come, which truly ſhows</l>
                  <l>Who is a <hi>Friends,</hi> they then become their <hi>Foes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Moſt, who pretend for GOD, that <hi>vertue</hi> fain</l>
                  <l>For nought; with them, is <hi>godlines,</hi> but gain.</l>
                  <l>They frequently, more bold with him do make,</l>
                  <l>Then with all others; and from him dare take</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:119976:30"/>
                  <l>What ere they can, to ſacrifice unto,</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Idoll;</hi> and ſuppoſe no wrong they do.</l>
                  <l>Yea, thoſe pert <hi>Jewiſh women,</hi> who had given</l>
                  <l>And, would <hi>give</hi> ſpice Cakes to the <hi>Queen of Heaven</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(And had befoold their Husbands to conſent</l>
                  <l>That, them they ſhould, in <hi>GODS</hi> deſpight, preſent,</l>
                  <l>Took not his Oyl, his pure Wheat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and his ſpices,</l>
                  <l>To make, their wicked wilfull <hi>Sacrifices,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With bolder impudence, then many a one</l>
                  <l>Among us, for this to Idols uſe have done.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>A <hi>Spirit,</hi> being, <hi>GOD,</hi> in no need ſtands</l>
                  <l>Either of <hi>Churches, Tithes,</hi> or <hi>Rents,</hi> or <hi>Lands,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Forms,</hi> or any of thoſe other things,</l>
                  <l>Which, for <hi>GODS</hi> worſhip, our <hi>devotion</hi> brings:</l>
                  <l>For, theſe will do his <hi>deity</hi> no good:</l>
                  <l>But, <hi>ſelfnes,</hi> is a God of <hi>fleſh,</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That will be highly pleas'd, with thoſe <hi>oblations</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>GOD</hi> Almighty, counts abominations,</l>
                  <l>If not made uſe of, with all circumſtances,</l>
                  <l>Which, in a right way, <hi>piety</hi> advances.</l>
                  <l>And, therefore, we do purpoſe (if we may)</l>
                  <l>To take them, for this <hi>Idol,</hi> quite away.</l>
                  <l>But peradventure, ere effect that finds</l>
                  <l>We may be taken hence, or change our minds.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, is in every heart, the <hi>Antichriſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which doth uſurp <hi>CHRISTS</hi> Temples, and reſiſt</l>
                  <l>His raigning there. There, <hi>paramount</hi> is he</l>
                  <l>(Though other <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> there, alſo be)</l>
                  <l>His chiefeſt oppoſite; and gives offence,</l>
                  <l>More then his <hi>Foes</hi> of greater eminence.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Devill,</hi> doth in the World, againſt him rant,</l>
                  <l>As his chief Foe; In his <hi>Church militant,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(At large) <hi>The man of ſin;</hi> And, <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Corruption</hi> in each individual <hi>State</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Congregation:</hi> But, <hi>this,</hi> hath alone</l>
                  <l>In every <hi>ſingle man,</hi> the <hi>ſupream Throne</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119976:30"/>
                  <l>Of <hi>oppoſition;</hi> though, ſometimes, appearing</l>
                  <l>In one <hi>beloved ſin,</hi> and ſometimes wearing</l>
                  <l>Another <hi>habit,</hi> as it beſt befits</l>
                  <l>The <hi>place,</hi> or <hi>perſon,</hi> where, inthron'd it ſits:</l>
                  <l>And, though the <hi>Devill, Turk,</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> and all</l>
                  <l>Whom, in their <hi>ſphears, The Antichriſt</hi> we call</l>
                  <l>Should down be thrown; we ſhal rejoyce in vain</l>
                  <l>If, in our <hi>hearts,</hi> this <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſtill raign.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This, is that <hi>Idol,</hi> which prolongs our woes:</l>
                  <l>This, is that <hi>Idol,</hi> which, if ere we loſe</l>
                  <l>Our preſent <hi>hopes,</hi> is that, which will effect it:</l>
                  <l>And, I do more then probably ſuſpect it.</l>
                  <l>This, is the laſt thing, my <hi>deceaſed friend,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Declaim'd againſt, before his latter end,</l>
                  <l>As likely to be that <hi>abomination,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which will occaſion here, a <hi>deſolation;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If not deſtroyed, or, at leaſt, debaſed</l>
                  <l>Within thoſe <hi>Temples,</hi> wherein it is placed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This <hi>Idol,</hi> hath in every heart a <hi>ſhrine;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, (though I hatert) doth poſſeſſe in <hi>mine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The <hi>inmoſt room;</hi> there, ſcrewed in ſo faſt,</l>
                  <l>That, thence, I fear, it hardly will be caſt</l>
                  <l>Till all that <hi>Fabrick</hi> ſhall be broken down,</l>
                  <l>VVherewith it is incorporated grown,</l>
                  <l>It knows what now I think, what now I <hi>write,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſticks the cloſer to me, in deſpight</l>
                  <l>Of all that I can think, or <hi>ſay,</hi> or <hi>do:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yea, and by means of this <hi>performance</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>The more exalted in my heart will be,</l>
                  <l>If, <hi>GOD</hi> himſelf, ſhall not deliver me.</l>
                  <l>But, he will add ſufficiency of <hi>Grace;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, I intend ev'n in that very place,</l>
                  <l>VVhere fixt it ſtands, to ſacrifiſe the <hi>Beaſt</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith all the <hi>trinkets</hi> of <hi>ſelf Intereſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVhich, if <hi>I</hi> can do, while 'tis fixed there,</l>
                  <l>VVill better pleaſe, then if <hi>deſtroy'd</hi> it were.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119976:31"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Another <hi>Virtue</hi> in my <hi>Friend,</hi> no leſs</l>
                  <l>Deſerving heed, was <hi>Conſcientiouſneſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>words</hi> and works; whereof, an imitation,</l>
                  <l>Would bring much happineſs unto this <hi>Nation.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For whiſe <hi>good Conſcience,</hi> entertain we ſhall,</l>
                  <l>It keeps a never-ending <hi>Feſtivall,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which gladdeth more the heart, then when we ſeaſt</l>
                  <l>To entertain our beſt beloved <hi>Gueſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If ſleighted; it becomes our greateſt <hi>Fo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If cheriſhed; it ſuch a Friend will grow,</l>
                  <l>That, when all elſe forſake us, and abuſe us;</l>
                  <l>When they oppreſs, and cauſleſly accuſe us;</l>
                  <l>When opportunity the <hi>Devil</hi> wins,</l>
                  <l>To muſter up againſt us, all our ſins;</l>
                  <l>When, <hi>GOD</hi> perhaps, doth lay upon us too,</l>
                  <l>A heavy hand: when <hi>Death</hi> (as it will do)</l>
                  <l>Arreſteth us, our <hi>countleſs debts</hi> to pay,</l>
                  <l>And, to his <hi>dungeon</hi> carries us away;</l>
                  <l>Ev'n then, when all our <hi>honors</hi> and our <hi>wealth,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>youth,</hi> our <hi>ſtrength,</hi> our <hi>pleaſures,</hi> and our <hi>health,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shrink from us: when, our <hi>beſt beloved Friends,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our <hi>wives</hi> and <hi>children,</hi> upon whom depends</l>
                  <l>Our greateſt earthly comforts, will forgo us;</l>
                  <l>Lodg us among the dead, where none ſhall know us;</l>
                  <l>And, leave us without ſuccour, all alone,</l>
                  <l>To give account for that which we have done:</l>
                  <l>Then, will this <hi>Friend,</hi> if well we cheriſh her;</l>
                  <l>(Yea, though ſhe formerly abuſed were,</l>
                  <l>If we be ſorrowfull for our offence</l>
                  <l>And reconciled by true <hi>penitence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will go along with us unto the <hi>Grave;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Remove all thence, whereof, we dread may have;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sleep</hi> there with us, whileſt there we ſhall remain;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Riſe</hi> with us, vvhen vve ſhall ariſe again;</l>
                  <l>And, make us there, vvith joyfulneſs appear</l>
                  <l>Before that <hi>Judge,</hi> vvhom other men ſhall fear:</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119976:31"/>
                  <l>For, having in this life, the privileges,</l>
                  <l>Of our <hi>Accuſers, Witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Which none elſe hath by our <hi>terreſtriall Laws,</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Before hand, ſhe determineth our <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She, by the <hi>Law</hi> that's vvritten in our hearts,</l>
                  <l>Doth judg us; and no jot from that departs;</l>
                  <l>So that no <hi>Soul,</hi> can juſtly counter-plead,</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Ignorance;</hi> or ſtand in any need</l>
                  <l>Of an Interpreter, or, <hi>witneſs</hi> brought,</l>
                  <l>To teſtifie, of vvhat, vvas <hi>good or nought:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, none, vvill ſhe condemn for that <hi>offence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereof, he bringeth not an evidence</l>
                  <l>Within <hi>himſelf,</hi> to clear, or to condemn.</l>
                  <l>For that, vvhich is objected unto them.</l>
                  <l>And, vvhoſoever to this <hi>judgment</hi> comes,</l>
                  <l>Shall blame <hi>themſelves,</hi> and juſtifie her dooms.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Look therefore that you <hi>keep</hi> this <hi>Judg</hi> your friend,</l>
                  <l>And that, by your fault, ſhe vvho vvill pretend</l>
                  <l>To be this <hi>Conſcience,</hi> be not entertain'd</l>
                  <l>Inſtead thereof: For, <hi>Conſcience</hi> may be ſtrain'd</l>
                  <l>So far, and by accuſtomed refuſing</l>
                  <l>Good counſell; and by vvilfully abuſing</l>
                  <l>Her juſt reproofs, till her avvay vve chaſe</l>
                  <l>And let an evil conſcience take her place.</l>
                  <l>And, vvhat events, may aftervvard enſue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> leave it, to be thought upon, by you.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hovv, vve may knovv a <hi>Conſcience</hi> rectifide;</l>
                  <l>Hovv, to preſerve it, vve may means provide;</l>
                  <l>How to recover it again when loſt;</l>
                  <l>Time to compoſe a large diſcourſe would coſt:</l>
                  <l>To ſound theſe <hi>depths, I</hi> therefore will forbear,</l>
                  <l>And onely add, for your example here,</l>
                  <l>What, by occaſion of my <hi>Friend,</hi> that's gone,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> have, ſince his departure, muſed on.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Good Conſcience,</hi> whereof high eſteem he made</l>
                  <l>Three <hi>Objects</hi> hath; to vvhich there muſt be had</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119976:32"/>
                  <l>A due reſpect, aſunder, and together,</l>
                  <l>Without neglecting, what belongs to either;</l>
                  <l>Except in things, wherein the <hi>leſs</hi> is debter,</l>
                  <l>To wave his due, for that, which is the <hi>greater.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>GOD</hi> is the <hi>firſt;</hi> our <hi>neighbours,</hi> or our <hi>brother</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(In ſome reſpects) the <hi>next;</hi> our <hi>ſelves</hi> the <hi>other;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe welfare, in ſome caſes, may before</l>
                  <l>The <hi>ſecond</hi> be preferr'd, and tender'd more:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, it is the <hi>Rule</hi> whereby to ſquare,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ove,</hi> which to our <hi>neighbours,</hi> we ſhould bear.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Our <hi>duties</hi> to all theſe, were in the <hi>heart</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Firſt written; and renew'd again, in part,</l>
                  <l>By <hi>common grace:</hi> But, <hi>ſin</hi> hath ſo defaced</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Table,</hi> and that <hi>writing</hi> ſo much raſed,</l>
                  <l>That, we muſt ſeek to make up that <hi>Record</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By what, <hi>GOD</hi> hath ſupplied in his <hi>Word;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, they, who would preſerve the <hi>conſcience</hi> fair</l>
                  <l>And blameleſs, to that <hi>Glaſs,</hi> muſt oft repair;</l>
                  <l>Which, (by that aid, which GOD to add will pleaſe)</l>
                  <l>Shews us, our ſeveral duties, to all <hi>theſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>All they, whoſe <hi>Conſcience</hi> is this way renew'd,</l>
                  <l>Know what ſhould be embrac'd, and vvhat eſchew'd.</l>
                  <l>Such, vvill not of his honour, God, bereave,</l>
                  <l>To ſave their <hi>Countrey;</hi> nor, their lives to ſave,</l>
                  <l>Spoil or betray that; nor, themſelves deprive</l>
                  <l>Of ought, vvhich they to ſerve <hi>theſe,</hi> did recieve</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>cowardiſe</hi> or <hi>ſloth;</hi> nor, to enjoy</l>
                  <l>The pleaſures of the <hi>fleſh,</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> deſtroy.</l>
                  <l>To <hi>GOD,</hi> they will not make a ſacrifice</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>guiltleſs blood;</hi> or, honour him vvith <hi>lies:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or, offer to him things achiev'd by ſtealth,</l>
                  <l>By fraud or rapine; nor their <hi>Common-wealth</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Repair, inrich, or ſtrengthen, by <hi>oppreſſions;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By tollerating any knovvn tranſgreſſions,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Piety</hi> deſtructive; or, to that</l>
                  <l>True <hi>Juſtice,</hi> vvhoſe defect, may ruinate</l>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119976:32"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Humane ſociety;</hi> either, by ſearing</l>
                  <l>To dravv their ſvvords againſt a <hi>Tyrants</hi> daring;</l>
                  <l>Or ſeeking, by a <hi>warlike way of murther,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hovv, to inlarge their <hi>territories</hi> further;</l>
                  <l>In hope of needles gain, or fruitles glory,</l>
                  <l>hais'd out of <hi>black deeds,</hi> by a <hi>bloody ſtory:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, proſecute the troublers of their peace,</l>
                  <l>Till <hi>ſafety,</hi> may be ſetled; and, then, ceaſe:</l>
                  <l>That, throughout all the World it may be knovvn,</l>
                  <l>They ſought not to inlarge, but ſave their ovvn;</l>
                  <l>And to diſable thoſe from doing vvrong,</l>
                  <l>Who, els, vvould all the World embroyl, ere long.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such, vvill not make their <hi>Publique Faith</hi> a ſcorn.</l>
                  <l>That they vvho live, and they vvho are <hi>unborn</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May in times future, be diſcourag'd from</l>
                  <l>Aſſiſting, vvhen another <hi>need</hi> ſhall come;</l>
                  <l>And, let all, rather unto ruine run,</l>
                  <l>Then truſt, vvhat is not to be truſted on.</l>
                  <l>Such, vvill not (as in times of need they may)</l>
                  <l>Take ſome mens lands, and lively hoods avvay,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Publique</hi> to ſecure, vvithout ſupply,</l>
                  <l>For loſſe of that, vvhich it vvas ſaved by:</l>
                  <l>But, to each <hi>private ſufferer,</hi> reimburſe</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>private damage,</hi> from the <hi>Publique purſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Such, vvill not miſemploy their <hi>Powr,</hi> in place</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>ſupream Truſt,</hi> unjuſtly, to diſgrace</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>faithfull ſervants,</hi> upon bare ſurmizes,</l>
                  <l>On miſreports, vvhich <hi>evill will</hi> deviſes</l>
                  <l>To blaſt their credit, ruine their <hi>Eſtate,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Perhaps their lives too) by objecting hate</l>
                  <l>Which is untrue- For, they not being there</l>
                  <l>Who could refute that, vvherevvith charg'd they vvere,</l>
                  <l>(Nor ſuffred to take notice, from vvhoſe tongue</l>
                  <l>They, in their abſence, did receive that vvrong)</l>
                  <l>A <hi>prejudice,</hi> doth bring a cenſure on them,</l>
                  <l>Which ere they can prevent it, hath undone them.</l>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119976:33"/>
                  <l>If they <hi>good conſcience</hi> have, who thus can do;</l>
                  <l>Ile think, the <hi>devill</hi> hath ſome conſcience too;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>How ſeared are the <hi>conſciences</hi> of thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Who, give their <hi>friends,</hi> much leſſe reſpect then <hi>foes?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obliging them by favours whom they fear,</l>
                  <l>VVould els be traytors, (or perhaps ſo are)</l>
                  <l>And diſoblige <hi>true men,</hi> becauſe, they know</l>
                  <l>No injury can make them leſſe then ſo?</l>
                  <l>VVhat conſcience, have they who do pretend,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Publique</hi> hath not, to releeve a friend</l>
                  <l>That's periſhing; and, yet the ſelf-ſame day</l>
                  <l>(Though no need were) profuſely give away</l>
                  <l>Large ſums among themſelves; and gratifie</l>
                  <l>Thoſe men, who with their faction do comply?</l>
                  <l>(And own their ways, opinions, and deſigns)</l>
                  <l>As if they did poſſeſſe, the <hi>Indian</hi> Mines?</l>
                  <l>VVhat <hi>Conſciences</hi> have they, who pay ſome worſt,</l>
                  <l>VVho merit beſt; and laſt, who ſerv'd them firſt:</l>
                  <l>Provide for thoſe; who for <hi>ſelf-ends</hi> do ſerve;</l>
                  <l>And let the <hi>Common-wealths</hi> true ſervant ſtarve?</l>
                  <l>Give ready Coyn to ſome; and unto them</l>
                  <l>Who did the ſame <hi>work,</hi> at the <hi>ſelf-ſame time,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not any thing at all? except, perchance,</l>
                  <l>A <hi>Warrant, Order,</hi> or an <hi>Ordinance</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which by begetting others, doth ſtill add</l>
                  <l>New troubles, and expence to what they had;</l>
                  <l>And without profit, ſo inlarge their coſt,</l>
                  <l>By pretious time, and redious labour loſt;</l>
                  <l>That, if at firſt, their debts they had forgiven</l>
                  <l>(And added ſo much more, to make all even)</l>
                  <l>To get a flat deniall; ſome, had gain'd</l>
                  <l>Much more thereby, then will be now obtain'd,</l>
                  <l>Though they were pay'd to morrow? One, <hi>I</hi> know</l>
                  <l>VVho by experiment, hath found it ſo;</l>
                  <l>Yet, ſome of them, who may this conſcience own,</l>
                  <l>Wo uld ſeem to think, great things on him, beſtown:</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119976:33"/>
                  <l>Becauſe, Gods mercy, other wayes ſupplies</l>
                  <l>That, which to him, their <hi>Juſtice</hi> yet denies.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What partiall <hi>Conſciences</hi> are alſo theirs?</l>
                  <l>Who, in eſtabliſhing of juſt <hi>Arrears,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Gave ſome full <hi>Intereſt</hi> for debts delay'd,</l>
                  <l>And none to others, for like debts unpay'd</l>
                  <l>Ten ſummers after; and, which may, before</l>
                  <l>They are diſcharg'd, ſtand charged ten years more</l>
                  <l>And then at laſt, perhaps, aſide be lay'd</l>
                  <l>Among thoſe debts, that never ſhall be pay'd?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From ſuch corrupted <hi>conſciences</hi> as theſe,</l>
                  <l>Hath ſprung our <hi>Epidemicall diſeaſe:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe many fold complainings, in our ſtreets,</l>
                  <l>Wherewith each friend his ſad companion greets:</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſcandals, which are publiſh'd in diſgrace</l>
                  <l>Of perſons, who were lately in the place</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sapream Truſt:</hi> hence, alſo, flows that hate</l>
                  <l>The Quarrels, diſcontentment, and debate,</l>
                  <l>Which is amongſt us: Hence, thoſe hazzards riſe</l>
                  <l>VVhich make us fearfull, and our Enemies</l>
                  <l>Still hopefull, that, it either ſhall occaſion</l>
                  <l>Some broyl <hi>within,</hi> or, ſome without <hi>Invaſion.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, if I may beleeve what my heart tels,</l>
                  <l>That, which they do expect, or ſomewhat els</l>
                  <l>Equivalent, vvill ſhortly come to paſſe,</l>
                  <l>If vve <hi>below,</hi> and they vvho are in place</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Above us,</hi> make not conſcience of our vvayes</l>
                  <l>More then vve have done, in preceding dayes.</l>
                  <l>For, if there be a GOD, as my ſoul knovvs</l>
                  <l>There is, by that, vvhich daily from him flovvs:</l>
                  <l>If there be <hi>devils,</hi> as I knovv vvell to,</l>
                  <l>There are by vvhat, <hi>I</hi> ſee their ſervants do.</l>
                  <l>GOD, or the <hi>Devill</hi> vvill to us appear</l>
                  <l>By ſome new <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> or <hi>work</hi> of <hi>fear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To purge hearts, from death procuring <hi>works,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that <hi>hypocriſie</hi> within them lurks;</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:119976:34"/>
                  <l>And keep us to the <hi>rule</hi> of doing <hi>ſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To others, as we would be done unto.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of which good practiſe, whilſt he here was living</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Weſtrow</hi> (having by examples of giving)</l>
                  <l>Deſerved to be a pattern, <hi>I,</hi> contrived,</l>
                  <l>This vvay, of having him, again revived;</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>I,</hi> and you, and others, by the light</l>
                  <l>From henoe reflecting, may walk more upright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lord, let theſe overflowings of my</hi> Spirit,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which, in themſelves have neither powr, nor merit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Produce forth good effects; and not be found</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Like that, which gives an uſeles, emyty ſound.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let it be ſome way, fruitfull unto them,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who had relations in the</hi> fleſh <hi>to him,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who, hereof gave</hi> occaſion; <hi>and, ſome way</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To every Reader, who peruſe it may;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, not a memorandum only be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To other men; but, likewiſe unto</hi> me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vouchſafe me grace, whilſt, here I live to ſerve</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>In this my</hi> Generation) <hi>not to ſwarve</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From my appointed</hi> work; <hi>but to perſever</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In doing it, with vigilant endeavour;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, of my</hi> Talent, <hi>when I muſt appear</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To give account (which time approacheth near)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I may be</hi> faithful <hi>found, and to that</hi> joy</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Admittance have, which nothing can deſtroy.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let neither</hi> fears, <hi>nor hopes, neglects, or wrongs,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deter from doing what to me belongs:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, though my</hi> faculty <hi>hath ſmall eſteem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And needles to the</hi> World, <hi>perhaps, may ſeem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In thoſe</hi> affairs <hi>which may be pertinent</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To thy great work: make it a ſupplement</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of ſome good uſe; that, times to come may ſee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My wither'd</hi> leaves, <hi>did help adorn the Tree</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>During that ſeaſon, wherein cloth'd it ſtood;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, were for cure of ſome diſeaſes good.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119976:34"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of what, in others, to be good, or ill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I have obſerv'd; let application, ſtill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So to my ſelf be made, that what I ſaw,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To be amiſſe in them, may me withdraw</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>From erring paths; and, in their ſteps to tread,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Who nave uprightly walk'd, (alive or dead.)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, I may truly</hi> foot thy meaſures, <hi>too,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As well as pipe them out, to thoſe that do:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Leſt, I my ſelf, a Reprobate be found,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>When all things have compleatly daunc'd their round.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let not the</hi> Revolutions, <hi>or the</hi> changes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or, that</hi> prevarication <hi>which now ranges</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Throughout the</hi> VVorld, <hi>me, from my</hi> ſtation <hi>carry;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or, cauſe me from good Principles to vary.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But, in the</hi> ſtream, <hi>of all thoſe great</hi> diſtractions,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diffring opinions, counter-marching actions,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plottings, deſignings, threatnings, and pertakings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whimſies, Chimeras, doubtings, and miſtakings,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fawnings, and frownings, praiſes, or diſgraces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Wants, and aboundings, in all times, and places,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So ſteddy keep my</hi> Judgment, <hi>and ſo clear,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, all my Life, I firmly may adhear</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To</hi> truth, <hi>and</hi> honeſty; <hi>and, plainly ſee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What</hi> man <hi>intends, or is deſign'd by thee,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, whatſoere, without me, makes a din;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let, me have alwayes, peace, and</hi> joy, <hi>within,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>My life, hath been a</hi> warfar <hi>to this day;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And troubles multiply: Yet, if it lay</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within my powr, to chuſe what other</hi> lot</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The beſt man living hath, (or I have not)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, might my ſelf, my own</hi> ſelf being <hi>make;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Let me no comfort, in my</hi> Portion <hi>take,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If, I, would chuſe ought els, but that which now</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I have, and thy</hi> free mercy, <hi>ſhall allow:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For, of thy</hi> love, <hi>ſo well aſſur'd am I;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:119976:35"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, how, thou beſt knowſt, what for me is beſt;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, on thy</hi> VViſdom, Powr, <hi>and</hi> Love <hi>Ile reſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I, love to ſee the doing what thou doſt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>Oh GOD! moſt</hi> holy, powrful, wiſe, <hi>and</hi> juſt)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, therefore, though my</hi> fleſh <hi>be terrifide</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By thy approaches, and, oft loth to bide</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Where, I may ſtand to ſee thee marching on,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And doing, here, ſuch things as thou haſt done:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yea, though ſometime, ſuch horrors on me ceaſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, they do ſhake my bones; yet naytheles,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My ſpirit, <hi>ſo is pleaſed, to behold</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thoſe</hi> Judgments, <hi>and thoſe</hi> mercies <hi>manifold,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which I obſerve; that, in no other</hi> time,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nor, (might I chuſe) in any other</hi> Clime,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Would I have liu'd, ſave where I might have ſeen</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Such things, as have to me diſcovered been:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>No, though thy</hi> Judgments, <hi>which, now on us be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Have in the</hi> fleſh, <hi>with others, wrapt up me,</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>For, whatſoever</hi> former times <hi>afford;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Whatever, hath been written in the</hi> Word;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What</hi> ſigns, <hi>or</hi> wonders, <hi>have been to thy glory</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Recorded in</hi> prophane, <hi>or</hi> ſacred ſtory;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hath been a new tranſacted, in my dayes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So, have I ſeen the</hi> River, <hi>and the Seas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Made paſſable: So, have I ſeen thy</hi> wonders</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>In</hi> blood, <hi>and</hi> Vermine; <hi>in</hi> fire, hail, <hi>and</hi> thunders;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, in thoſe other dreadfull</hi> ſigns, <hi>whereby</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thou, heretofore didſt</hi> Pharaoh <hi>terrifie;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Myſteriouſly, or morally (at leaſt)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If not in all things, lit'rally expreſt:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, have abſerv'd, that, they on other men</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Have now, the ſame effects, which they had then.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To</hi> carnal wiſdom, <hi>but events of chance</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>They do appear; and, ſuch, to ignorance.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Great</hi> Kings, <hi>and</hi> Princes, <hi>will not yet be wiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But fool themſelves, with</hi> vanities, <hi>and</hi> lies;</l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:119976:35"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, are like</hi> Pharaoh, <hi>daily hardned ſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As if they dared thee, thy worſt to do.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yea, their</hi> inchanters, <hi>though they cannot ſtand</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Before thee, (and acknowledg 'tis thy hand,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which is upon them) do endeavour ſtill,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To ſeek themſelves, and to reſiſt thy</hi> will.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, all of us, almoſt as heedles are,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of what thou doſt, as</hi> Jacobs <hi>off-ſpring were.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thy</hi> judgments, mercies, threatnings, promiſes;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſeverall</hi> cauſes, <hi>and</hi> effects <hi>of theſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Have been to me,</hi> exemplifide <hi>a new,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By that, which hath been offred to my view:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Th' occurrances, betwixt thy</hi> Friends, <hi>and</hi> Foes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Long time ago, foretipifying thoſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That ſhould ſucceed, (and, were for</hi> Preſidents,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That like</hi> proceedings, <hi>would have like</hi> Events</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Throughout all ages) I've ſeem parallel'd</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>By thoſe, which with mine eyes, I beheld:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, by thoſe</hi> tipes, <hi>compar'd with what I ſaw,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Did, ſometimes from them ſuch</hi> concluſions <hi>draw,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, I foretold, when few beleeved me,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>What, they and I, have liv'd, fulfil'd to ſee.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, though, thou art not pleas'd to let me know,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Perſpicuouſly, what is approaching now:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Yet, I ſee</hi> dim appearances, <hi>whereby</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I may ſuſpect a</hi> miſchief <hi>drawing nigh.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> Cloud, <hi>which like a</hi> mans hand <hi>ſeems to be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Or, els, a</hi> mans hand, <hi>like</hi> a Cloud <hi>I ſee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Threatning a</hi> ſtorm. <hi>I ſee, me thinks, Ob</hi> Father!</l>
                  <l>Vapours <hi>far off diſperſt, begin to gather</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Into divided bodies, whence may break</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A</hi> voice of Thunder, <hi>and things dreadfull; ſpeak,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With ſad events; If we with ſpeed repent not;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And,</hi> thou, <hi>the</hi> plagues, <hi>which we deſerve, prevent not.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oh! therefore, turn our hearts; and unto thee</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So, from our own wayes let us turned be,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:119976:36"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That, thou maiſt ſtill continue thy</hi> compaſſion,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>With thy accuſtom'd</hi> favours, <hi>to this</hi> Nation.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And, my beloved <hi>Brethren,</hi> for whoſe warnings,</l>
                  <l>I, thus adventure my dim <hi>fore-diſcernings</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To publique cenſure, though not for my ſake,</l>
                  <l>(For your own ſafety, notice of them take:</l>
                  <l>And, of your vanities, repent with ſpeed;</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>Judgments,</hi> but conditionally decreed,</l>
                  <l>May be averted: And, that, thoſe <hi>good things,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of whoſe approach the <hi>ſeaſon</hi> ſymptoms brings,</l>
                  <l>Deferred may not be: For, there is, yet,</l>
                  <l>Somwhat, to be <hi>removed,</hi> which doth <hi>LET,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Kingdoms</hi> coming, for which, many pray;</l>
                  <l>And, that <hi>Removall,</hi> muſt prepare the <hi>Way.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If, GOD,</hi> this <hi>way,</hi> by <hi>judgments,</hi> muſt inforce,</l>
                  <l>It will, for us, now living, be the worſe;</l>
                  <l>And, we ſhall bear the ſtrong pangs of that <hi>BIRTH</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, that myſterious <hi>WOMAN</hi> will bring forth,</l>
                  <l>On whom, the <hi>DRAGON</hi> waiteth to devour</l>
                  <l>The <hi>MANCHILD,</hi> who (deliver'd from his power</l>
                  <l>By his <hi>Almighty Father,</hi> and our <hi>GOD</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Shall rule the <hi>Nations,</hi> with an <hi>IRON ROD.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, if we willingly remove from hence,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>LET;</hi> it ſhall produce a <hi>recompence,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which will requite our labour, and deſtroy</l>
                  <l>The great <hi>Obſtructer</hi> of our promis'd <hi>Joy.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here, <hi>I</hi> had done. But ſomwhat, preſſeth in,</l>
                  <l>On which, <hi>I</hi> could anew again begin.</l>
                  <l>It doth not much concern my <hi>Theam, I</hi> know;</l>
                  <l>But, what, of that? It may concern you, tho.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Muſe,</hi> oft times, when ſhe is on her wings,</l>
                  <l>Wheels from her Game, to unexpected things</l>
                  <l>Which come to view; and, thereby more hath won</l>
                  <l>Somtimes, then if aſide ſhe had not gone.</l>
                  <l>So, may ſhe now; Ile therefore, let her fly</l>
                  <l>At what ſhe ſees, although <hi>I</hi> know not why.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:119976:36"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>Kingdom</hi> look'd for, ſeems to be near</l>
                  <l>By many tokens, which to me appear,</l>
                  <l>As well upon the <hi>Governments</hi> of thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who, there to are profeſt, or ſecret <hi>Foes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As on the <hi>SAINIS:</hi> For, when I was but young,</l>
                  <l>(And ever ſince my <hi>child-hood,</hi> all along)</l>
                  <l>I, thereto had an eye: And, in this <hi>clime,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Or <hi>little world</hi>) I've ſeen within my time</l>
                  <l>Four <hi>Governments,</hi> almoſt as differing</l>
                  <l>Both in the <hi>roots,</hi> from which they forth did ſpring,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>diſcipline,</hi> as <hi>DANIELS Monarchies:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, much, to be conſider'd, in them lies,</l>
                  <l>To make me to beleeve, that, <hi>CHRIST</hi> is ſhaking</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Worlds foundations;</hi> and, approaches making.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The firſt was, when much ſam'd <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Raig'nd here; In whoſe time, (though I drew my breath</l>
                  <l>Not thirteen years) I, obſervations made</l>
                  <l>Of things, then ſaid and done, both <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>bad,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>More then my age did promiſe; and, er'c taught,</l>
                  <l>Was to the beſt part, of my <hi>knowledg</hi> brought.</l>
                  <l>During this <hi>Monarchy, I</hi> did perceive,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sincerity,</hi> begin to take her leave;</l>
                  <l>That, <hi>Chriſtian zeal</hi> abate, and cool again.</l>
                  <l>Which was ſo hot, when ſhe began to Raign;</l>
                  <l>And, introductions of ſuch <hi>deviations,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As, both forego, and foreſhow <hi>alterations.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, that, which then did ſeem to keep in aw</l>
                  <l>Theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> was, the <hi>GOSPEL,</hi> and the <hi>LAW.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Next her, out from the <hi>Caledonian Wood,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>ramping Lyon</hi> came; and, up he ſtood.</l>
                  <l>As, he firſt got this pow'r, he kept the ſame,</l>
                  <l>By acting of the <hi>Fox,</hi> and ſeeming tame.</l>
                  <l>To his devourings, he impos'd no meaſure:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Law</hi> he govern'd by, was <hi>WILL,</hi> and <hi>PLEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, he purſude, what he deſign'd at firſt,</l>
                  <l>As far, as any <hi>craſty coward</hi> durſt.</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119976:37"/>
                  <l>More ſtoutly, his <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> carried on,</l>
                  <l>Then politickly, what his <hi>SIRE</hi> begun;</l>
                  <l>And after many ſtruglings, and much coſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Himſelf,</hi> his <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>deſigments</hi> he loſt.</l>
                  <l>Yet, for that <hi>Government,</hi> thus much Ile ſay,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>piety,</hi> wore in that day,</l>
                  <l>The faireſt <hi>out-ſide;</hi> and, were trim'd about</l>
                  <l>With many <hi>Ornaments,</hi> now, nigh worn out;</l>
                  <l>And, <hi>goodnes,</hi> had a very glorious <hi>ſhell,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Although the <hi>kernels</hi> therein prov'd not well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Againſt this <hi>Government,</hi> the People roſe,</l>
                  <l>In throaning them, whom they themſelves had choſe;</l>
                  <l>And whilſt they were continu'd on the <hi>Throne,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>NECESSITIE,</hi> was law, for what was done:</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Law,</hi> to lengthen, and corroborate,</l>
                  <l>They, new <hi>NECESSITIES</hi> did ſtill create;</l>
                  <l>Till their <hi>Adorers,</hi> did their Pow'r contemn,</l>
                  <l>And, found great need of all things, but of <hi>THEM.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, by indulging <hi>ſelfnes,</hi> they deſtroy'd,</l>
                  <l>What had by <hi>ſelf-deniall</hi> been en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oy'd;</l>
                  <l>And made themſelves ſo rich, and ſome ſo poor,</l>
                  <l>That, now, the <hi>Peoples choice,</hi> is out of dore.</l>
                  <l>Yet, whilſt they kept the <hi>Throne, GOD,</hi> by them wrought</l>
                  <l>Effects, which will not wholly come to nought:</l>
                  <l>For, though <hi>ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> moſt prevailed then,</l>
                  <l>There were among them, <hi>good, and righteous men,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(To <hi>GOD,</hi> and to their <hi>Country</hi> ſerviceable)</l>
                  <l>Whoſe <hi>number,</hi> had it been proportionable</l>
                  <l>To <hi>ten,</hi> for each five <hi>Cities, Towns,</hi> or <hi>Shiers;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had made the <hi>work,</hi> reſerv'd for others, theirs.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The <hi>SWORD,</hi> hath now, obtain'd the <hi>ſoveraign pow'r,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let it, Oh <hi>LORD!</hi> protect, and not devou'r.</l>
                  <l>Let, it take notice, that it is prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Vineyard,</hi> only, to ſecure and gard,</l>
                  <l>(Or, cut away thoſe Plants, which might annoy</l>
                  <l>The fruitfull <hi>Vines,</hi> and their ſweet grapes deſtroy)</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:119976:37"/>
                  <l>Not to poſſeſſe the ſame as if it own.</l>
                  <l>Let us (although the <hi>pow'r</hi> thereon beſtown,</l>
                  <l>Should be abus'd) obediently attend,</l>
                  <l>Till to the <hi>raign,</hi> thereof, thou ſetſt an end:</l>
                  <l>For, when thou pleaſeſt, thou, canſt in one hour,</l>
                  <l>Make it deſtroy it ſelf, by it <hi>own Powr.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>To rule us, thou haſt now advanced it;</l>
                  <l>Let us, for conſcience ſake, therefore, ſubmit,</l>
                  <l>Whether it be for <hi>future good,</hi> or <hi>ill;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Becauſe, to have it ſo, it is thy <hi>will.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou canſt as well by <hi>Arms,</hi> as by the <hi>Gown</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Rule peaceably, and make thy <hi>mercy</hi> known.</l>
                  <l>Although it be a <hi>Sword,</hi> that bears the ſway,</l>
                  <l>Let, it thine <hi>Adverſaries,</hi> only, ſlay;</l>
                  <l>Let none of thine, have any cauſe to fear it:</l>
                  <l>And, let it no wayes dammage thoſe that wear it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Still, mindfull make it, for whoſe good, and ayd</l>
                  <l>'Twas firſt advanced, diſciplin'd, and payd:</l>
                  <l>Who, did contribute, what, firſt, made it ſtrong</l>
                  <l>To conquer: who, ſtill adds, what doth belong</l>
                  <l>To keeping of that <hi>Powr;</hi> and, let it not</l>
                  <l>Indanger thoſe by whom it was begot;</l>
                  <l>Wrong their <hi>propriety,</hi> whom it defended;</l>
                  <l>And whoſe juſt preſervation was intended;</l>
                  <l>Nor, breake thoſe antient <hi>bounds</hi> which kept ſhould be</l>
                  <l>'Twixt <hi>man</hi> and <hi>man;</hi> and, betwixt <hi>man,</hi> and <hi>Thee;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, upon whoſe <hi>Infringers</hi> thou haſt laid,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Curſe,</hi> whereof, all, ought to be afraid.</l>
                  <l>Let it perform the works thereto appointed;</l>
                  <l>Make way for <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and for thy <hi>Anointed:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And, when the time deſign'd thereto is done,</l>
                  <l>Let it, to what muſt follow, yeeld the <hi>Throne.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The next, I hope ſhall be the <hi>LIVING-WORD.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let his long look'd for <hi>KINGDOM</hi> come, Oh <hi>LORD!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let over us, that <hi>King of Nations</hi> raign,</l>
                  <l>To whom, all <hi>praiſe,</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> doth pertain.</l>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:119976:38"/>
                  <l>For, whatſoer'e this proves, that beſt will pleaſe us.</l>
                  <l>Come therefore, quickly Quickly come, <hi>LORD JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Mean while, accept a ſacrifice of <hi>praiſe,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For what hath been vouchſafed in theſe days,</l>
                  <l>By way of <hi>preparation,</hi> to that <hi>End,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For which, in <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> we do attend.</l>
                  <l>Accept of pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes, from the <hi>ſingle hearted,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For all thy <hi>Saints,</hi> which are from hence departed;</l>
                  <l>And, for all thoſe, who ſhall make up the ſum,</l>
                  <l>By which thy Kingdom, will compleat become.</l>
                  <l>Accept my <hi>Thanks,</hi> for what thou didſt confer</l>
                  <l>On me, by him that's gone, and thoſe, yet here:</l>
                  <l>Accept it rather, for that <hi>love</hi> of thine,</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafed from thy ſelf, to <hi>me</hi> and <hi>mine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By frequent <hi>pledges;</hi> and, for that <hi>Free grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whereby before all time, <hi>I</hi> choſen was,</l>
                  <l>To be eternally made One with Thee;</l>
                  <l>And, in thy <hi>ſelf,</hi> accept them <hi>LORD,</hi> of me.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="envoy">
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thus, having my</hi> Friends <hi>Obit, truly truly kept.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Six nights, <hi>(whilſt others round about me ſlept)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here, that</hi> Contexture, <hi>which conceiv'd I had,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Is now produced,</hi> ſpun, <hi>and</hi> weav'd, <hi>and</hi> made.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>'Tis true the</hi> Object, <hi>of my</hi> contemplations,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Was WESIROW: But, from him, my</hi> Meditations,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Roſe higher; and my ſoul did contemplate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Things, which conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n theſe</hi> Nations, <hi>and this</hi> State;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And, thereupon, ſome</hi> hints, <hi>are interweaved,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which will (if paſſed by, as unperceived).</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Make th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap> which is, the</hi> Muſes <hi>way of giving</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Life <hi>to the </hi> Dead; <hi>to be, unto the</hi> Living,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An</hi> on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> preſage; <hi>at leaſt to ſome,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of</hi> death, <hi>of</hi> ſhame, <hi>or, of worſe things to come.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119976:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
